<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Natures dowrie: or The peoples native liberty asserted. By L.S.</title>
            <author>L. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S111</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E668_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206988</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866066</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866066</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118326</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92496)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118326)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 102:E668[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Natures dowrie: or The peoples native liberty asserted. By L.S.</title>
                  <author>L. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 60 [i.e. 61]   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W.R. at the signe of the Vnicorn in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 1 is on A2v. With page 13 repeated in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Running title: The peoples native liberty asserted.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 29".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monarchy --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118326:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Natures Dowrie:</hi> OR THE PEOPLES NATIVE LIBERTY ASSERTED.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Art thou called, <hi>being</hi> a ſervant? care not for it: but if thou mayeſt be made free, uſe it rather,</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 Cor. 7.21.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>Ovis non eſt propter paſtorem; ſed paſtor ovi inſervit.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Warneri Proverb. Perſ. 16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Quin et mortalem ſummum fortuna repentè</l>
                     <l>Reddidit, è ſummo ut regno famul optumus eſſit.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fortune the low ſoon lifts to th' high'ſt degree,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That made great Kings they ſhould good ſervants be.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <bibl>Ennius <hi>VIII.</hi> Annali.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>By <hi>L. S.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. R.</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Vnicorn</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1652.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118326:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:118326:2"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Treatiſe, I aſſure thee, is no more dipp'd in paſsion, then the Sunne is drowned in the clouds, which are ſo far below him. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it deſired, whilſt he aſſerted other mens liberty, himſelf to be ruled by reaſon, bearing in mind that ſentence, <hi>Reges alios, ſi ratio te rexerit, Thou ſhalt govern others, if reaſon guide thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was occaſioned by a question, which a worthy Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber both of the Parliament and Committee of State above three years ſince propounded to me. Within ſhort time after I provided this anſwer, and at my firſt opportunity preſented it unto him. He judged that it deſerved to be made of publick uſe, and offered it to the Preſs; yet <hi>Lucina</hi> was not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious as to bring it to light; the Printer not daring to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it, unles the Author had been preſent to ſuperintend the work. I publiſh this diſcourſe after I have ſo long ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed it, becauſe the uſefulneſſe thereof is ſtill in date, in that it explaneth many Scriptures which are ſtill by many wrested into falſe ſenſes: and becauſe there is now a more convenient opportunity then formerly. Farewell.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>L. S.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118326:3"/>
                  <head>Natures Dowrie, <hi>OR,</hi> The Peoples Native Liberty aſserted, &amp;c.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> Certain Theſes concerning the freedom, and authority of any Nation.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas ſome have concluded that an abſolute <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie</hi> is the beſt of Governments, becauſe it imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateth that by which God ruleth the <hi>Univerſe;</hi> I conceive their reaſon is feeble and impotent; and that they conſidered not that men may abuſe their authority and power, which liberty is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to God.</p>
                     <p>All authority, unleſs God determine otherwiſe by chuſing out one or more to rule over the reſt, (which now a dayes we have no reaſon to expect) is fundamentally and radically in the people.</p>
                     <p>A conquered people, unleſs they be obliged to the Conquerour, by conſenting formerly to be ſubject to him, in their own perſons, or in their Fore-fathers; or after the conqueſt voluntarily took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them his yoke, without conditions, or elſe upon ſtipulation; are warranted by the light of naturall reaſon to endeavour the recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their liberty: and likewiſe after a compoſition, when the Conquerour in his own perſon, or in his poſterity, neglecteth the terms upon which they ſubmitted to him.</p>
                     <p>That Kings ſhould be <hi>ex ſe uati,</hi> (as <hi>Tiberius</hi> ſaid of <hi>Curtius Rufus</hi>) <hi>That nature or conqueſt ſhould be a ſufficient title to domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and that an illegall force may not by force be lawfully removed;</hi> are opinions which the clear light of reaſon never ſmiled upon.</p>
                     <p>Should any one with<note n="*" place="margin">Tacitus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Tiberius,</hi> be <hi>ſine miſeratione, ſine irâ, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatus, clauſuſque ne quo adfectu perumperetur,</hi> by a reſerv'd and mercileſs obſtinacy ſhut up, and baracado'd againſt the lawes, counſell and prayers; I ſee not but a people may warrantably goe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118326:3"/>about to break ſuch an one, ſeeing he will not be bended by reaſon.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Monarchy is not by Divine right.</head>
                     <p>I Shall in the firſt place ſhew that Monarchicall Government is not of abſolute neceſſity,<note place="margin">'The <hi>Peravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> have thus much notice of the generall deluge, that the Country was overwhelmed with waters, &amp; all men pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed except ſeven. The chief of theſe ſeven was <hi>Mangoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga,</hi> whoſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſelves for ſome time in <hi>Ariſtocr at i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> ſtate. See <hi>Heylyn</hi> in his Deſcription of <hi>Peruana,</hi> I cannot aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to <hi>Diodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Siculus,</hi> telling us (<hi>Bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioth, Hiſt.</hi> l. 2.) that there were Kings in <hi>Aſia</hi> long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ninus,</hi> eſpecially if (as ſome Authors conceive) his <hi>Ninus</hi> be the ſame with <hi>Nimrod.</hi>
                        </note> I mean not here a phyſicall neceſſity (for to ſuch a Monarchy cannot pretend) nor a neceſſity of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action (ſeeing that excludeth choice) but a morall neceſſity hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon the Law of God. Moſt clear it is, that neither the Law of Nature, which is written upon the tables of mens minds by the finger of God, nor yet any poſitive Law which God ſuperadded to the Law of Nature, determineth any Nation to that form of Government. Turn over the Scripture, which hath omitted none of Gods commandements that are now in force, and ſhew me a precept for it. None will be ſo impudent as to affirm that there is any expreſſe commandement for Monarchy in the written word of God: neither is there ſo much as a ſhadow of any <hi>Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> (or <hi>Conſequentiall</hi>) injunction thereof; unleſs it be clear by natural reaſon that Monarchy is the beſt of Governments for all Nations at all times, howſoever their circumſtances varie. It is clear (I acknowledge) both by the light of Naturall reaſon, and by the Scripture, that men are bound in Conſcience to prefer that form of Government, which they know to be the beſt for them. but that Monarchy ſhould by the light of naturall reaſon be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to be the beſt of Governments, and that for all Nations, and at all times, I cannot conſent; becauſe the world after the flood till <hi>Nimrods</hi> days<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Nimrod</hi> was a <hi>mighty hunter</hi> before the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.9. For the underſtanding of that phraſe, compare with this Scripture, <hi>Ier.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Lament.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.2. <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.17. That of <hi>Arist.</hi> in the firſt of his Politicks, is a good comment likewiſe upon <hi>Nimrod's</hi> hunting; <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, &amp;c.</note> had no Monarch, neither oeccumenicall, nor provinciall; and becauſe Monarchy then came into the World, not by choice<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> informeth us that the Kings of <hi>Aegypt</hi> were in all their actions confined by their Lawes, and particularly, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. Biblioth. Hiſtor. l. 1. The ſame Hiſtoriographer, ſpeaking of the K. of the <hi>Aethiopians,</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. Biblioth. Hiſt. l. 3.</note> but by intruſion &amp; uſurpation, by force &amp; conqueſt;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118326:4"/>becauſe the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had a mixt Government; and the moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing States amongſt the Papiſts, and all reformed Churches, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſuch Heatheniſh Commonwealths as have moſt aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in perſpicacitie and wiſdom, have ever preferred other forms of Government before it. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> likewiſe determineth (<hi>Polit.</hi> 3.) that a King ought to have power to protect the Lawes, but not ſuch power as may render him more potent than the Kingdom.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> The main argument which oppoſeth what I have delivered in this Chapter, is bottomed upon part of the 7th. comma of the 4. Chapter of <hi>Gen.</hi> which in our tranſlation ſaith, <hi>Anà unto thee</hi> ſhall be <hi>his deſire, and thou ſhalt rule over him.</hi> The Argument propounded in full dimenſions, hath this ſtature.</p>
                     <p>That civil government, which God inſtituted in the beginning of the World, ſtandeth by divine right throughout all ages. But God inſtituted abſolute Monarchie in the beginning of the World. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Aſſumption ſeemeth to be warranted by that Scripture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore produced.</p>
                     <p>God (ſay my Antagoniſts) gave to the eldeſt Sonne after his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers death, Monarchicall authority over his brethren. Into this ſenſe they conſtrue that ſentence, <hi>And unto thee</hi> ſhall be <hi>his deſire, and thou ſhalt rule over him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> The propoſition of the ſyllogiſm before exhibited, is very impotent: neither can I divine with what crutch my Antagoniſts can ſupport it.</p>
                     <p>There is not the like reaſon for Monarchy in after-ages, as in the infancy of the world, unleſs it be as caſie for one man to govern a Nation, as to govern a Family. There was truth, though no ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity in that ſpeech of <hi>Tiberius, ſe in partem curarum ab Auguſto vocatum, experiendo didiciſſe, quàm arduum, quàm ſubjectum fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae cuncta regendi onus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Kings which God appointed the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> after they had caſt off him from ruling over them, were not abſolute Monarchs.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall now explain, whether thoſe words before quoted (in <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.7.) warrant what was aſſumed, to wit, a divine inſtitution of Monarchy.</p>
                     <p>The words in the Originall are capable of this conſtruction, <hi>The deſire of it</hi> (that is, of ſin) is <hi>unto thee, but thou ſhalt rule over it.</hi> Compare <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12. The affixes (I confeſs) differ in <hi>gender</hi> from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118326:4"/>the word for <hi>ſin;</hi> but ſo alſo doth <hi>robets,</hi> the word for <hi>lieth. Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> well obſerveth other ſuch differences in other texts of Scripture.</p>
                     <p>Amongſt the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Scholiaſts <hi>Raeſi, Bechai, Nachmanides,</hi> and <hi>Abarbinel,</hi> as alſo the Author of <hi>Thargum Jeruſ.</hi> are very full for that ſenſe which I have propounded. According to theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters <hi>teſchukatho,</hi> which in our Engliſh tranſlation is, <hi>his deſire,</hi> meaneth the <hi>deſire of ſin,</hi> to wit <hi>jetſer haraugh,</hi> an <hi>evil frame</hi> or <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> of ſoul and<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>jeiſer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raugh</hi> is not by the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the minds, though by many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Authors it be rendered <hi>mala cogitatio. Abarbinel</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that place in <hi>Gen.</hi> before quoted, having before inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted <hi>tejchu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kah</hi> to be <hi>jetſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> haraugh,</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>becauſe the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy inciteth a man to ſin.</hi>
                        </note> bodie, (we call it <hi>concupiſcence,</hi> which fitly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preteth the word <hi>teſchukah</hi>) which (ſay they) inſtigated and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Cain</hi> to ſin, and which he ſhould vanquiſh, would he repent. <hi>Becanus</hi> is clearly of the ſame ſenſe; <hi>Dixit Dominus ad Cain: Nonnè, ſibene egeris, recipies; ſin autem malè, statim in foribus peccatum tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um aderit? ſub te erit appetitus ejus (peccati ſcilicet) &amp; tu domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beris illius (appetitus ſcilicet quo ad peccatum propendes, &amp; alliceris.)</hi> Thus the Author now quoted, <hi>Theol. Scholaſt. part.</hi> 2. <hi>tract</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 50.</p>
                     <p>But let us ſuppoſe the affixes of the ſentence quoted to be referred to <hi>Abel,</hi> who is not mentioned in the 5.6. nor in the preceding part of the 7. verſe, yet cannot the word for <hi>deſire</hi> in this verſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a ſubjection of <hi>Abel</hi> to his Brother <hi>Cain</hi> as an abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, or a King.</p>
                     <p>In <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16. it is ſaid of <hi>Eve, thy deſire</hi> ſhall be <hi>to thy huſband; and he ſhall rule over her.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Polit. 1.</note>
                        <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> telleth us, that a man <hi>ruleth his wife and his children, but both as thoſe who are free</hi> (or not ſervile.) <hi>But not with the ſame manner of Government</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.) <hi>but his wife politically, and his children after the manner of a King.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The word for <hi>deſire</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ainſworth</hi>) implieth a <hi>deſirous affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> as appeareth by <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.10. The Apoſtle ſeemeth to allude to it in 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. Whereas <hi>Onkelos,</hi> for <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>and ye ſhall be as Gods,</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>and ye ſhall be as Princes,</hi> (which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable enough to the Originall) the Serpent by <hi>Gods,</hi> not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the S. Trinitie, as <hi>Eve</hi> conſtrued him, but the faln Angels, who whilſt they ſtood, had experimental knowledge of good, and ſince their fall, of evill; and which are called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118326:5"/>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">ſee alſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.15. and <hi>Eph.</hi> 2 2. where <hi>the Prince of the Air,</hi> or <hi>of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> (for <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> will alſo without wreſting, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction) may fitly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſignifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>the chief of the faln An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or all the faln Angels.</hi>
                        </note> according to our Engliſh tranſlation, <hi>principalities, powers,</hi> and rulers of the darkneſs of this world, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12.) <hi>Abarbinel</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Vpon <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.5.</note> conceiving him to ſpeak of earthly Princes ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Onkelos</hi> here is not to be allowed, becauſe then there were no Princes in the world: which words (I conceive) are not to be determined preciſely to the time in which the Serpent tempted <hi>Eve,</hi> but to be extended to the whole time of <hi>Adams</hi> life, if not to all the time before the Flood. But I ſhall ſeem to have ſpent needleſs labour in diſcovering the weakneſſe of the <hi>Minor,</hi> ſeeing there is not the like reaſon for Monarchy now as in the beginning of the World: and eſpecially (which I deſire all men to take notice of) in that the authority which they attribute to <hi>Cain</hi> over <hi>Abel,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth us as firm an Argument for an <hi>abſolute Monarchy of the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Sonne over his brethren</hi> throughout all ages, as for Monarchie to be continued in the World.</p>
                     <p>The authority of the eldeſt Sonne over his brethren which God inſtituted in the beginning of the World, ſtandeth by divine right throughout all ages.</p>
                     <p>But God in the beginning of the World appointed the eldeſt Sonne to be an abſolute Monarch over his Brethren. <hi>Ergo,</hi> Every eldeſt Sonne in every age (and ſo now a dayes) is an abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch (after his Fathers death) over his Brethren.</p>
                     <p>Let none therefore henceforth, who force that Scripture for the aſſertion of Monarchy, dare to affirm, That any one by divine right ought to have larger authority over others, then every el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Sonne after his Fathers death hath over his brethren.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Monarchy is ſo far from ſtanding by divine right, as that it falleth ſhort of ſome other forms of Government.</head>
                     <p>MOnarchy is worſe then ſome other governments, 1 Becauſe one cannot diſcern ſo much as many of equall parts.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Object.</hi> It may be objected, that this reaſon implieth that all in a Commonwealth who have attained to years of diſcretion, ought to be admitted to Vote about every State-buſineſs.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> I deny the conſequence; in that the managing of all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick affairs by the Votes of the whole people, eſpecially in popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118326:5"/>Commonwealths, is a thing altogether impoſſible: both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it would almoſt wholly withdraw men from their private concernments, and likewiſe retard the diſpatching of thoſe buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in which they have a joynt-intereſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, &amp;c. Ariſt. Po.lit. 3.</note> Becauſe there are but few in compariſon, who are able to judge in State affairs. Thoſe who are themſelves unfit for that taske, may be able to make choice of others ſufficiently accompliſhed.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Becauſe when the Monarch is wicked, the Government of the State muſt needs be evill, in that he is not divided againſt himſelf; becauſe he will not act againſt himſelf: but when Authority is betruſted with many, the good, though fewer, ſometimes out-wit the reſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Plato</hi> (in his 9 <hi>de legibus</hi>) perceived the weight and moment of this and the preceding reaſon, telling us, that <hi>it is neceſſary for men to appoynt Laws and to obſerve them; unleſſe they be min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did to differ nothing from the moſt ſavage Beaſts.</hi> And aſſigning this cauſe thereof, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c. No man is by Nature ſo accompliſhed, as that he may be able to diſcern what things conduce moſt to the publick good; and when he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what is beſt, alwaies be able and willing to perform it, <hi>Plato</hi> pointeth theſe reaſons in his enſuing diſcourſe.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Becauſe there is more reaſon to fear that one man, then that a whole multitude ſhould be malignantly affected. <hi>Ariſtatle</hi> telleth me (<hi>Polit.</hi> 3. c. 11.) that as much water cannot ſo ſoon be vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated as a leſſer quantity; ſo neither are a multitude ſo eaſily as one man corrupted in their judgment by anger, or any other paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. His words are theſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> Here it may be objected that we have more reaſon alſo to hope that one man, then that a multitude will be well-affected.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. I anſwer, The more authority and power any one hath in his hands, by ſo much he is more tempted to acts of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. An abſolute Monarch, who hath no law but his own will, may more eaſily miſcarry, then thoſe who have onely their porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Government of a Nation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> 2. There is far more danger from an ill-affected Monarch,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118326:6"/>then when onely part of thoſe who are in authority, are vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Becauſe no one will dare to ſay unto an abſolute Monarch, what doeſt thou?<note place="margin">When <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſes</hi> inquired of his Lawyers, whether there was any Law which permi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing, to marry his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fler? they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That they found no Law, which permitted a Brother to marrie a Siſter: but that they found another Law, <hi>v.z.</hi> that it was lawfull for the King of the <hi>Perſians</hi> to do what he pleaſed. See <hi>Herodo'us</hi> in his <hi>Thalia.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>And one who never heareth that queſtion from another, it is much to be feared, will forget to propound it to himſelf. He will be ready to conceive that with <hi>Iupiter,</hi> he hath <hi>Therius</hi> perpetually placed by him, ſo that whatſoever he doth, muſt needs be right and juſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iezebel</hi> thought it a queſtion unbeſeeming a Princely ſpirit. She concluded that <hi>Ahab</hi> drooped below himſelf, when he boggled at the taking away of <hi>Naboth's</hi> vineyard. <hi>Memento mihi omnia &amp; in omnes licere.</hi> Thus <hi>Caius</hi> in <hi>Suet mius.</hi> I may adde, That a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy ſet led in any one for term of life, is more dangerous, then if the time were limited.</p>
                     <p>Thoſe who expect that their authority ſhould expire before their lives, will be reſtrained in ſome meaſure by a fear of their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors who may call them to an accompt, in caſe they manage not their truſt as it becometh them. Thoſe who are to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt only to God, are tempted to licentiouſneſs, in that men are not wont to be much awed by an inviſible Magiſtrate. <hi>Plato</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth us, that when any one (<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>) is not bound to give an accompt (of his actions and omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) but governeth a City as he lifleth, (without any controller) he cannot perſiſt in ſuch a mind throughout his life, as to preferre the publick good before his private advantage.<note n="*" place="margin">Plato 9. de leg.</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. 4. <hi>That</hi> One man ſhould have a larger ſhare in the Government of a State then all the reſt who are intereſted therein, <hi>is not enjoyned by the Word of God.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>A King is not a neceſſary ingredient of the Government of a State. Were a true and viſible King of abſolute neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had ſinned in that throughout ſo many ages after they came into the Promiſed-Land, they ſet not a King over them. We muſt taxe many other well-ordered States of a ſin of omiſſion in point of civill government, if we underprop the Scepter by <hi>divine right.</hi> As a King is not neceſſary by virtue of any divine precept, ſo neither in order to the well-managing of civil affairs: as the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118326:6"/>flouriſhing condition of many States which are without Kings, aſſureth us.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> The neceſſity of Tribunals is evinced.</head>
                     <p>I Shall in this Chapter, that I may make way. for my enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, explain the neceſſitie of Judges and Tribunals. The <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonian Gemara</hi> of the Tractate called <hi>Sanhedrin,</hi> in the 7 Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, telleth us, That <hi>as God injoyned the Iſraelites to ſet up judiciary Courts in all their villages and cities, ſo likewiſe he commanded the Sons of Noah to erect Tribunals in all their villages and cities.</hi> The place is quoted by learned <hi>Selden</hi> in that incomparable work <hi>De ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Natural. &amp; Gent.</hi> l. 7. c. 5. This Law they muſt needs affirm to be given to thoſe who lived before the deluge, as well as to <hi>Neah's</hi> poſterity, ſeeing they make it part of the Law of Nature. The <hi>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of fleſh with the life thereof</hi> was as unlawfull for <hi>Adam</hi> and the reſt of the old world, as for thoſe who lived ſince the Flood; but needed not to be forbidden to them explicitly <hi>viva voce,</hi> (as <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.4.) in that they were not permitted at all to eat fleſh. The <hi>ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting apart of ſome time for Gods worſhip</hi> is injoyned by he law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and was in ſome degreee put into practice by Gods children from the Creation,<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>See</hi> Seder. Olam Rabba c. <hi>5.</hi> Philo de v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. tà Meſis <hi>l. 1.</hi> Tertull. adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Judaeos. A hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſ. in Synopſi ſacr. Scrip. <hi>upon</hi> Exod. Euſeb. Demonſtrat. Evangel. <hi>c. 6.</hi> Juſtin. Hiſt. lib. <hi>36.</hi>
                        </note> though the Sabbath was not obſerved till the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> came into the Wilderneſs.</p>
                     <p>That (<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>) <hi>Houſes of Iudgments,</hi> or <hi>Tribunals,</hi> ſhould be conſtituted for all people, is clearly part of the Law of Nature. For otherwiſe that puniſhment which the Law of Nature demandeth for certain offences, as murder, &amp;c. could not be regularly executed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Plato</hi> (in his 9. book of Lawes) in ſeverall caſes appointeth thoſe that are naturally allied to the perſon that is murdered, to inflict death upon the murderer; and ſo likewiſe ſome of the kindred of the partie raviſhed, to kill the raviſher.</p>
                     <p>But theſe conſtitutions border upon the making a man a Judge in his own cauſe. If any one be killed by chance-medley, thoſe whoſe affections Nature hath engaged to the perſon that is ſlain, will be tempted to miſconſtrue it into murder.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jacob</hi> curſed the wrath of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> who revenged the raviſhing of their Siſter <hi>Dinah</hi> upon the <hi>Sechemites,</hi> Gen. 49.7. Suppoſe alſo thoſe who ſuſteined the greateſt loſſe in the partie murdered, to neglect the executing of puniſhment: the city or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118326:7"/>Country, in which it was committed, is expoſed to Gods wrath for bloodſhed which goeth unpuniſhed.</p>
                     <p>We ſhall be more at a loſs in the executing of penalties for the breach of ſome other of the precepts which are ſaid to be given to <hi>Noah,</hi> as idolatry and blaſphemy, and the eating of fleſh with the life thereof; unleſs tribunals be erected.</p>
                     <p>In theſe offences the wrong is not done eſpecially to this or that man, nor this or that Family, but immediately to God the Lord of all, and by way of reflexion in regard of Gods wrath, and by bad examples, to the whole people.</p>
                     <p>The main argument which ſeemeth to inferre that <hi>Tribunalls,</hi> or the exercize of civil judicature, is not inforced by the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is, that <hi>it was not ſo from the beginning.</hi> In the Sacred Hiſtorie of the World before the <hi>deluge,</hi> we have no inſtance of any humane cenſures. And<note n="*" place="margin">Metam. l. 1.</note> 
                        <hi>Ovid</hi> telleth us that thoſe who lived in the <hi>firſt</hi> or <hi>golden age, erant ſine judice tuti.</hi> His meaning (I conceive) is, that <hi>they were free from humane cenſures.</hi> That which this Author in his deſcription of the <hi>golden age,</hi> delivereth to this purpoſe, maketh me much ſuſpect that for ſome conſiderable time after the Creation, there were no Courts of juſtice eſtabliſhed: nor any humane cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; whether by the eldeſt of a Family, or by the multitude, or any autorized to that purpoſe. In his work now prayſed, we may often diſcern a truth recorded in the Scripture, through the cloud of his Poetrie.</p>
                     <p>In the beginning of his firſt book, we have the Hiſtory of the Creation; and in that, <hi>man</hi> laſt of all created. His <hi>Gygantomachia</hi> was occaſioned by the building of the Tower of <hi>Babel.</hi> He menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneth alſo the <hi>deluge;</hi> That piece of his Poetrie took its riſe from <hi>Noahs Flood:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">☞</note> For it was not confined to this or that patch of ground, but overwhelmed all mankind, ſave <hi>Deucalion</hi> and <hi>Pyrrha-Lucian</hi> alſo telleth us, that <hi>Deucalion</hi> with his Wife and Children were ſaved in a great Ark which he had; and that two of every kind of living creatures came to him, and were received into the Ark, and preſerved in it. And <hi>Plutarch</hi> maketh mention of a Dove ſent by <hi>Deucalion</hi> out of the Ark, and bringing newes of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement of the waters. In the beginning of his 8 book we have <hi>Samſon's</hi> hair given to <hi>Niſus</hi> In the ſame book we have the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and the change of the ſoyl thereabout: and <hi>Let</hi>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118326:7"/>with his Wife under the names of <hi>Philemon</hi> and <hi>Baucis,</hi> fetched out thence by Angels, under the Poeticall vizard of <hi>Jupiter and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury.</hi> We have <hi>Lots</hi> inceſt alluded to in <hi>Cynaras</hi> and <hi>Myrrha,</hi> l. 10. In the beginning of the 12. book <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> when ſhe was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened to the Altar, and about to be ſacrificed, is changed for a Doe: which ſhadoweth out unto us <hi>Iſaac</hi> excuſed for a Ram. In the ſame book <hi>Cygnus</hi> ſlaying 7000. men, and feigned to be impene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trable, is a reſemblance of <hi>Samſon.</hi> In that I find ſo much of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſtorie in this Poet, I conjecture that his Poem about the four ages hath ſome tincture from holy writ. The Image which <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> ſaw in his dream, is one ingredient of it: and mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity before his fall, another<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Salmaſ. de U u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>is,</hi> c. 11. p. 303.</note>: and the condition of mankind for ſome time after our fall, a third. It was uſuall with the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then (as we may obſerve both from their Poets, and<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Juſtine,</hi> l. 36. <hi>Tacitus,</hi> Hiſtor. lib. 5.</note> Proſaicall writers, and from thoſe two excellent treatiſes written by a late Author which diſcover unto us the <hi>Banian</hi> Religion, and the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the <hi>Perſees</hi>) to mangle thoſe truths which are contained in the Word of God, and likewiſe to confound, and blend them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: which is very familiar likewiſe with the pen-men of the <hi>Alcoran.</hi> But it is eaſie for the moſt part to perceive the Sun through their clouds. I ſhall eaſily grant that men for ſome time after their fall in our firſt Parents, lived after their own man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, being reſtrained by no Courts of Juſtice: but we cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre from thence that ſuch Courts are not neceſſary: nor yet that they are not by divine right. God might out of his ſecret counſell for ſome time connive at ſuch an omiſſion: after what manner he permitted the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> writing a Bill of Divorce, to put away their Wives:<note n="*" place="margin">Thoſe who lived in the former times of the World, ought to have ſet out ſome time for God, in which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants might have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from ſuch works, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>re not of neceſſity, nor charity, nor piety.</note> or as he connived at the ſetting of no certain time apart for his worſhip, till himſelf made choice of a day when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were brought into the Wilderneſs: or as for a long time he connived at Polygamie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Other juriſdiction is neceſſary now a dayes, beſides that wherein the Law of Nature hath inveſted Maſters of Families.</head>
                     <p>THe next queſtion to be diſcuſſed, is, whether the exerciſe of juriſdiction be confined by a birth-privilege to certain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.<note n="*" place="margin">Polit. l. 1.</note> 
                        <hi>Every houſe is governed by the Eldeſt,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118326:8"/>as alſo the colonies</hi> (which are propagated from it) <hi>in regard of their</hi> (<hi>cognation,</hi> or) <hi>kindred.</hi> But clear it is that now a dayes au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority cannot be diſpenced according to this principle.</p>
                     <p>We have no records by which we can be informed who by way of inheritance and birthright, as all are reckoned from <hi>Noah,</hi> ſhould have a preeminence above the reſt. Neither can one man (though <hi>Firmicus</hi> telleth us that a certain poſiture of the Starres deſigneth a man to an univerſall Monarchie) be ſo <hi>Atlantick,</hi> as to bear upon his ſhoulders the government of the Univerſe. Nor yet can it be known, who in this or that Country in regard of a deſcent from <hi>Noah,</hi> ſhould have advantage of the reſt in order to juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and government. Neither are the Eldeſt alwayes the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt.<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Diodorus Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus</hi> (B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>blict. Hiſt. lib. 3.) ſpeaking of the Inhabitants of an Iland in the Southern Ocean, ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. The eldeſt in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry company beareth rule over it, as a King: and all the reſt obey. Though there be a vaſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between bearing ruſe over a certain company of men, (whether their aſſociating of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together take its riſe meetly from the harmonie of their minds, or from their occupation) and the goverment of a Nation; yet no wiſe man will conceive that their practiſe is perpetually to be imitated.</note> Thoſe who manage the publick affairs of any people, ought to be ſuch as have <hi>animi vires, &amp; ſtrict as pondere mentes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That ſentence of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> before praiſed is to be underſtood of a Family living apart from the reſt of mankind; as<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>See</hi> Tulliein O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. pro P. Sextio, Juvenal Salyr. <hi>15.</hi>
                        </note> did ſome in the firſt Ages of the World, and for ſome generations after the Deluge, and perhaps upon ſome extraordinary occaſions in later times. But that any Maſter of a Family at any time before the Flood paſſed a ſentence of death upon any appertaining to his Family, cannot be proved out of any monuments of antiquity now extant. Neither doth it appear, whether <hi>Iudah</hi> pronounced ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death upon <hi>Thamar</hi> by virtue of any authority which he had over her as belonging to his Family, or by virtue of ſome Law conſented to by his Fore-fathers, or according to the Law and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Countrey in which he lived, or out of raſhneſs. Some of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors affirm that <hi>Iudah</hi> intended not that <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> ſhould be burned to death, but only ſtigmatized in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head for an harlot.</p>
                     <p>What authority ſoever a Maſter of a Family may challenge by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118326:8"/>the Law of nature over his children and ſervants, and thoſe who by mariage are ingrafted into his Family, whilſt he is a ſojourner among a Nation into which he is not incorporated; clear it is that thoſe who have their ſhare in any Country, and a ſetled abode a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others, have no title to ſuch authority, in that they are temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to partiality, and may expoſe their neighbors to divine juſtice, by neglecting judgments, or by giving unjuſt ſentence of death, and the ſame wayes weaken the Country in which they live, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to a common enemy. <hi>Homer</hi> (in the Iota of his <hi>Odyſſ.</hi>) maketh it a badge of rude and uncivill people, to live together in the ſame Countrey, and not to imbodie themſelves into a Society, nor have any publick juriſdiction; ſaying of the <hi>Cyclopes,</hi>
                        <q>
                           <l>— <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>They give lawes every one of them to his Wives and children, neither regard one another.</hi> Moſt agreable it is to the light of Nature, that thoſe who inhabite the ſame Countrey, and ſo nigh together that they are without inconveniencie capable of a common government, ſo combine and aſſociate the ſtrengths of their minds and eſtates, as that they may be<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Herodotus</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Thracions,</hi> who by ſome are called <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, becauſe every man w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> a Law to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: that if they had either, been all of one mind, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one K. they had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible.</note> in a poſiture of defence againſt a common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and home-bred diſturbances: which cannot be effected with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out common lawes, and publick execution of juſtice.<note n="*" place="margin">Plato de Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus, <hi>l. 9.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                     <p>Men muſt of neceſſity eſtabliſh lawes, and obſerve them, or not at all differ from the moſt ſavage beaſts.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> Magiſtracy ſtandeth by divine right.</head>
                     <p>IT remaineth doubtfull, whether people who live together, may lawfully retain an Iſocracie among them, having all of them ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages of equall value in the cenſuring of Delinquents, and the managing of ſuch affairs as conduce to their publick ſafety; or be bound by the law of Nature, or any of Gods poſitive lawes to ſet Governors and Magiſtrates over them?</p>
                     <p>We inquire not now of Magiſtracy fettered in the circumſtances of <hi>hic</hi> and <hi>nunc,</hi> determined to time and place; (for there is no doubt but among the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> not only Magiſtracy, but alſo certain forms of Magiſtracy were by divine right; moreover that certain perſons alſo bare rule among them by divine right, and that without the mediation of any humane choice) nor yet of Magiſtracy during the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118326:9"/>time for which it is eſtabliſhed by men, that is, of Magiſtracy with a preſuppoſition of humane conſent, by which in ſome form or other it was erected, and is for ſome time to be continued: ſeeing that Gods Law requireth that men ſtand to their agreements, and the Scripture ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
                        <hi>The powers that be, are ordained of God;</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note> 
                        <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake:</hi> but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God hath commanded all Nations at all times to have Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Judges, or State-Officers? The queſtion is, that I may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther explain the ſtate of it; whether Iſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>raſie be lawfull, or men be bound by the Law of God to ſet up a Magiſtracy, to preferre ſome to bear rule over the reſt? The Scripture doth not extricate us in this controverſie by any generall precept. Nor yet if we ſearch the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the World before the Flood, ſhall we find any foot-ſtep of Magiſtracy, or of humane cenſures. We have much wickedneſſe mentioned in the groſs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. and ſome ſins ſpecified elſewhere, but no intimation of any puniſhment inflicted by any humane judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature.<note n="*" place="margin">The murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of <hi>Abel, Gen.</hi> 4.8, and according to ſome Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters murder committed by <hi>Lamech, Gen.</hi> 4.23. and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry according to ſome of the Hebrew Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.26. I ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the two places laſt quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; but <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mech</hi>'s raſh ſpeech deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a cenſure. We have Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygamie like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>v.</hi> 19. of the ſame chap. but which ſome deny to have been a ſin in <hi>Lamech.</hi>
                        </note> That of <hi>Cain, It ſhall come to paſs, every one that findeth me ſhall ſlay me,</hi> importeth not that he feared any judiciary ſentence; but only a rude and boyſtrous inflicting of puniſhment; that it was permittted to every one to puniſh ſo hainous a delinquent: and that he expected not any regular proceedings of juſtice againſt him. But I take notice that in regard of the preſent, he feared where no fear was, departing from the preſence of his Parents; neither was likely to prophecie after what manner puniſhments ſhould afterwards be diſpenced. I conceive, he expreſſed a fear of men onely, and not of beaſts. His ſpeech was raſh and inconſiderate, having a tincture from his guilty conſcience.</p>
                     <p>If we conſult with the light of reaſon, it will inform us that in large countryes Magiſtracie is neceſſary; becauſe in ſuch the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants (though all who are ſervile and indigent be excluded) cannot convene ſo oft as virtue is to be rewarded and encouraged, or as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders are to be repreſſed, and vice to be puniſhed; nor yet ſo oft as the preſervation of their common ſafetie requireth.</p>
                     <p>It is clear alſo from the written word of God, that all publick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs ought to be managed in ſuch a way as may conduce moſt to Gods glory and the publick good.</p>
                     <p>Moreover God appointed a few in his own peculiar people to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the reſt. Such likewiſe at all times hath been the cuſtom almoſt of all Nations.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118326:9"/>
                     <head>CHAP. <hi>8.</hi> The qualifications of thoſe who ought to vote in the diſpencing of Authority. The major part of ſuffrages is equivalently the whole number. Thoſe who are uncapable of Voting, are tied to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ARiſtotle</hi> well obſerveth,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. Polic. 3.</note> that all are not Citizens who inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit the City, ſeeing Strangers and Servants have their ſhare in habitation.</p>
                     <p>He frequently excludeth thoſe who are indigent, from bearing ſway in a Commonwealth. Vnequall it is that Helots and thoſe who have no eſtates, ſhould have equall authority with thoſe who are wealthy, in making Laws which concern mens eſtates; in that by their private condition they are much tempted to favour theft and encroachment.</p>
                     <p>Seeing men are by an innate and hereditary diſtemper biaſed towards wicked practices; indigent people who are not reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from injuſtice by any ſelf intereſt, but on the contrary temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to rapine and perfidiouſneſs, are altogether unfit to manage the publick affairs of a Nation. If they have power in their hands, they are fit to ſqueeſe their neighbours; or if they want power themſelves, through envy and hope of ſharing in the prey, ready to betray them to foreiners, if an opportunity be offered. Good nature excepteth ſome, and Religion others in Chriſtian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths from this rude and barbarous diſpoſition: but the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter which I have given, fitteth the moſt of thoſe who are indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in every nation. It neceſſarily followeth, that they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to be truſted with a Legiſlative power, or offices of judicature and government, or to Vote in the choice of thoſe to whom ſuch authority and power ſhall be committed.</p>
                     <p>It remaineth that only ſuch as have an ingenuous ſubſiſtence in the Country to be governed, have a title to vote in the diſpencing of authority, whether for the preſerving of the whole body from forein invaſions, and homebred tumults, or for the reſtraining of vice, and encouraging of virtue. Neither ought any ſo qualified to be debaried from that privilege, unleſs they have diſcovered
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118326:10"/>themſelves to be malignantly affected towards the publick good.</p>
                     <p>Whereas thoſe who chooſe State-officers, and ſuch alſo as by their votes immediately order the publick affairs of a City, or Country, are apt to be divided among themſelves, in that they differ in their judgments, and in their ends; the light of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon telleth us, that the major part of the ſuffrages is equivalent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the whole number.</p>
                     <p>It cannot be expected that all the members of a Societie ſhould agree about the means which are moſt effectuall to the promoting of their publick welfare: Neither can the leſſer number of thoſe who have equall authority, be of more value than, or of equall with the greater. That ſtrife may be avoided, the number of thoſe who ſuffrage muſt be odde, or elſe ſome one of them have a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting voice granted him, in caſe the numbers of thoſe who are divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, be equall: and the major part of the ſuffrages muſt bear ſway, as if the reſt concurred with them. That Maxim, <hi>(Quod ad omnes ſpectat, ab omnibus debet approbari,) What concerneth all, ought to be approved by all;</hi> is ſatisfied, by a conſent of the greater part, which is equivalently the whole number. If a leſſer part of thoſe who vote, forcibly reſiſt a greater; unleſſe that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the prevailing number of votes, be repugnant to the Law of God, they infringe the Law of Nature, and likewiſe the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Law of God; and ſo have no reaſon to expect that God ſhould goe along with them in their enterpriſes.</p>
                     <p>More doubtfull it is, whether thoſe Inhabitants of a Citie, which are upon due grounds debarred from bearing Office, and from the choice of Officers, be bound in conſcience to ſubmit to thoſe who are inveſted in lawfull authority; and to the wholeſom Laws which are enacted by thoſe who according to the Law of nature have a Legiſlative power, either fundamentally, or elſe derivatively re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding in them.</p>
                     <p>Whereas Gods Law leaveth men indifferent to ſeverall courſes which may be taken for the preſervation of their lives, and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and livelihoods; when they have once conſented that one certain courſe not repugnant to the word of God, and convenient for the obtaining of any of theſe ends, ſhall be uſed: and have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118326:10"/>compromitted to any perſon or perſons the executing of their Law: God requireth that they ſubmit to the perſon, or perſons, to whom they have betruſted authority, till their grant expire, ſo he or they tranſgreſſe not the bounds of the Commiſſion, but execute the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement.</p>
                     <p>But the Queſtion is, whether thoſe who are hindered from vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the molding and forming of the government of the City which they inhabite; be obliged likewiſe to ſubjection?</p>
                     <p>The truth of the negative part being ſuppoſed, thoſe who did not agree to a Law enacted, neither directly, nor yet virtually, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the major part of thoſe who voted; ſhould not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by God's Commandements to ſubmit to that Law, as it is the Law of man: though they be obliged to obſerve the matter of it, when it is contained likewiſe in the Law of God.</p>
                     <p>Men by virtue of the 8. precept, are warranted to defend their eſtates according to their abilities, were there no humane Law ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peradded: and ſhould have no further advantage according to the former ſuppoſition, by ſuperadding an humane law, againſt ſuch as were not permitted to vote in the enacting thereof, but only that they agree to preſerve their livelihoods anſwerably to the Law of God, againſt all who ſhall invade them. They might without any former Law or agreement warrantably vindicate one another from injuries, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did <hi>Lot;</hi> but moreover are by an agreement mutually ingaged.</p>
                     <p>But I conceive that ſuch of the people, as have title to vote in the choice of a Repreſentative, or of other Governors, or by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves immediately to eſtabliſh Lawes; have another advantage againſt thoſe, who by the meanneſs of their condition, or by their miſdemeanors, are debarred from thoſe privileges.</p>
                     <p>Foraſmuch as the meaneſt Inhabitants of a City reap ſome bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit from the well-tempered government thereof; moſt equall it is that they ſhould ſubmit unto thoſe Laws which conduce to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of publick ſafety. And foraſmuch as God hath exempted none who offend, from humane cenſures; Some are bound to be accomptable for their demeanors to the Magiſtrate, who by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence, or by their own delinquency were rendered unfit to have an influence into the choice of him. God requireth that evill doers be puniſhed: but hath left unto men the ſpecifying of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118326:11"/>the puniſhment, whether it be capitall, or more gentle. Such then as are juſtly hindered from voting about the kinds of penalties that are uſed in the City which they inhabit: when they offend, muſt ſuffer in ſuch a way as is agreed upon by others. The will of God is, that thoſe who have done evill, ſubmit to lawfull pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, rather than reſiſt lawfull authority.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. <hi>9.</hi> All Civill Authority, unleſs God determin other wiſe, by chooſing out one or more to Rule over the reſt: which now a days we have no reaſon to expect, is fundamentally and radically in the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</head>
                     <p>WHereas ſome tell us of an abſolute <hi>Monarchie</hi> before the <hi>Deluge;</hi> I conceive with the beſt Hiſtorians, that none can prove that there was any ſuch Government in the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Nimrods</hi> incroachment and uſurpation. We have no ſhadow thereof intimated in the written word of God; nor in any humane writing of approved credit. Had any one before <hi>Nimrod</hi> uſed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall authority, it is probable the Scripture ſhould have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us notice thereof; as it doth of <hi>Nimrods</hi> Tyranny.</p>
                     <p>But clear enough it is, that although there ſhould have been Kings, otherwiſe than as every man is a Prince over his own fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; to wit, ſuch as reign now a dayes; before the deluge, yea ſo ſoon as the World through the encreaſe of mankind was capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſuch: they could have no ſufficient title to reign, unleſs through Gods immediate choice, or by the choice of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
                     <p>Conqueſt, unleſs the Conquerour was provoked by ſome inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,<note n="*" place="margin">It is not the firſt blow that maketh the War Invaſive, (for that no wiſe Prince will ſtay for) but the firſt <hi>Provocation,</hi> or at leaſt the firſt <hi>Preparation.</hi> See the Ambaſſage of <hi>Charles</hi> the 8th. the <hi>French</hi> K. to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, K. of <hi>England;</hi> in the Lord <hi>Verulam's Henry the ſeventh.</hi>
                        </note> or reall dangers, ſuch as were a juſt occaſion of a warre; can give no better a title to authority, than theſt to another mans goods. Neither ought the Conquerour, though he was provoked to the War, to uſe violence, longer than it ſhall be neceſſary for the ſecuring of himſelf from violence.<note n="†" place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118326:11"/>
                     <p>Succeſſion in a Kingdom, which hath it's riſe from a Conqueſt, unleſs the conſent of the People ſupervene; is no better a title than mere Conqueſt: ſith a continuance in doing wrong, cannot make that which is <hi>Wrong,</hi> to become <hi>right.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When God maketh choice of Governors for a people, he ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth the Peoples authority, but taketh it not quite away: they have liberty to diſpence authority, ſo ſoon as God ceaſeth to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe.</p>
                     <p>When a Monarchy, or Ariſtocracie is founded upon the Peoples choice, the authority is actually in one, or ſome few; but radically in the People.</p>
                     <p>If any incroach, and uſurp authority by force, the right ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in the people: greater thefts no more than leſſer, aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the right or title to the thing which is invaded.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Solon,</hi> though he permitted not ſuch whoſe revenue amounted not to ſo much as 200 meaſures of aride and liquide fruicts, (who were called <hi>Thetes</hi>) to bear any Office in the Common-wealth; yet gave them authority to be preſent in the Aſſemblies of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to vote (in the chooſing of Officers, and) in matters of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature. And he ſuffered thoſe to appeal to the people, who thought they were wronged by the Magiſtrates. See <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Solon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But this perhaps was to prophane authoritie by immoderate popularity.</p>
                     <p>Whereas <hi>Demetrius</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Antigonus,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Gonates,</hi> after he had reigned a ſhort time, left a young ſonne called <hi>Philip:</hi> the <hi>Macedonians</hi> preferred one <hi>Antigonus</hi> Coſin to the deceaſed King, to be King <hi>Philips</hi> Protector, and the chief manager of his warlike affairs, but after having experience of him,<note n="*" place="margin">Plutarch <hi>in his</hi> Paulus Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius.</note> made him their King.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Timoleon,</hi> when he had delivered <hi>Syracuſa</hi> from former tyrannie, made it a free City: as <hi>Plutarch</hi> witneſſeth in his life.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Plutarch <hi>in the life of</hi> Marcus Cato.</note>The <hi>Roman</hi> Cenſors, one of which was a Patrician, the other a Plebeian: had power to degrade a Knight; or to eject any one out of the Senate, who lived intemperately and diſorderly.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Plutarch <hi>in the life of</hi> C. Marius.</note>The Senators of <hi>Rome,</hi> when <hi>Saturninus</hi> was <hi>Tribune</hi> of the People; ſware that they would obſerve, what the People ſhould vote.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118326:12"/>
                        <q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Agamemnon</hi> in <hi>Euripides</hi> ſaith of himſelf;</l>
                           <l>
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>.</l>
                           <l>
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>.</l>
                        </q> which Sentence I find thus tranſlated in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Interpreter of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in the life of <hi>Nicias:</hi>
                        <q>
                           <l>In outward ſhew of stately pomp, all others I exceed,</l>
                           <l>And yet the Peoples underling I am in very deed.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> Kings agreeably to the Law of God, may in ſome Caſes be forcibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by their Subjects; and likewiſe depoſed.</head>
                     <p>A Competency of the light of naturall reaſon will diſcover (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be overcaſt with paſsion) that it is as lawfull for a conquered People by violence to recover their Libertie, as it is for any man to extort his goods out of the hand of a Felon, who is running away with them: as it was for <hi>David</hi> to reſcue his goods and wives out of the hands of the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> who had plundered <hi>Ziglag.</hi> Scarce any will dare to affirm that poſſeſsion is ſufficient to give a juſt title.</p>
                     <p>Neither is it leſs clear that a conquered people, which ſubmitted upon termes to the Conqueror, whether in their own perſons, or in their forefathers; are no longer engaged to ſubjection by their ſubmiſsion, than the Conqueror, and his Succeſſors obſerve the Conditions, upon which ſubjection was promiſed. The Peoples promiſe in their ſtipulation cannot pretend to bind them any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, than the terms upon which they promiſed, are obſerved. Were it otherwiſe, there ſhould remain no difference between an abſolute, and a conditionall ſubmiſsion.</p>
                     <p>I acknowledge, if the infringement of the conditions on the Conquerours part be in ſuch particulars onely, as are not momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to the impairing of the publick welfare, and there be no danger of further encroachment: much more if there be a likelihood of redreſs and reparation:<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. Ariſt. Polit. lib. 2.</note> Eſpecially when violent proceedings
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118326:12"/>threaten greater diſadvantages to the preſent age, or to ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding generations: it is better for the People to continue in ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, than to endeavour a change.</p>
                     <p>In ſome caſes it may be their prudence to pardon their Prince not obſerving his ſtipulation: but their promiſe is out of date, and cannot bind them to further ſubjection.</p>
                     <p>A People, whoſe Anceſtors have for themſelves, and their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, either gratis, or upon inconvenient articles promiſed ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and obeiſance to any one and his heirs; may lawfully (as Mr. <hi>Cnox</hi> and <hi>Bachanan</hi> well perceived) renounce the ingagement, and caſt off the yoak.</p>
                     <p>Gods proceedings with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Sauls</hi> breach of Covenant with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> have ſeemed unto ſome to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the negative.</p>
                     <p>God puniſhed <hi>Saul</hi> in his poſterity for violating that Covenant, which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> againſt his commandement before their paſſage over <hi>Iordan,</hi> had made with the <hi>Gibeonites.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here it may be anſwered, that although a People be bound to obſerve a bad Covenant made by their fore-Fathers, which is not much inconvenient, yet in ſome caſes it may be neceſſary that the Covenant be broken.</p>
                     <p>Learned Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> intimateth, that ſuch agreements made by a People, as are repugnant to the Law of God, whether na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall or poſitive, do not bind, <hi>De Iure Naturali &amp; Gentium jux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Diſciplinam Ebraeorum.</hi> l. 1. c. 8.</p>
                     <p>Should any by their own, or by their fore-Fathers Oath, ſtand ingaged to the obſervance of ſuch Laws as eſtabliſh Heatheniſm, Mahumedaniſm, Iudaiſm, or Popery; ſuch a Law cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin be kept, and may without ſin be violated.</p>
                     <p>Civill inconveniencies which accrue through the obſervance of a Covenant, may riſe ſo high as to warrant the reaſſuming of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
                     <p>If any Prince go about to deſtroy Religion, he affordeth unto his ſubjects a juſt occaſion of reſiſting him.</p>
                     <p>If Religion be eſtabliſhed by an humane Law, the Prince may be queſtioned for incroachment in caſe he oppoſe it, as well as for vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olating other terms of his agreement with his people.</p>
                     <p>It may be Objected, That the infringment of ſuch a Law,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118326:13"/>though it violate the Princes agreement and conſent to that Law; yet perhaps may not encroach upon the conditions for which the People promiſed ſubjection to him.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 I Anſwer, That no People ought to ingage their ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to another, unleſs he condeſcend to be regulated by thoſe Laws to which he ſhall give his conſent: and in caſe they accept of any one for their King upon other terms, their poſterity are not bound to ſtand to ſo imprudent a compact.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 That ſhould a people be guilty of ſuch an omiſſion in their ſtipulation with a Conquerour, or any whom they ſhould prefer to bear rule over them; his conſenting to a Law which is for their advantage, is an act of grace and favour, by which he deveſteth himſelf of ſome part of his prerogative, which was ſetled upon him by his firſt agreement with the people, and addeth it unto their privileges, ſo that a Law may be called an additionall ſtipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. And were it otherwiſe, it would ſcarce be worth his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects labour to meet for the enacting of Laws, ſith their Prince ſhould be left free to diſpence with them at his pleaſure.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 A Law which is beneficiall to the ſubject, giveth him an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in ſome privilege, for which he may contend as lawfully as for any thing elſe which is his own. And it ſeemeth clear to the light of reaſon, that any one who hath power, may defend his own by the ruine of an incroacher, when otherwiſe he cannot be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure.</p>
                     <p>The controverſie touching reſiſtance to be made againſt a Prince, who oppoſeth Religion, when it is not eſtabliſhed by an humane Law, is more perplexed.</p>
                     <p>Suppoſe a Prince to make it his ſtudy to give a check-mate to Religion; or, though he affect not an utter extirpation thereof, yet by his good will to allow it no exiſtence but with ſubordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his own deſignes. Suppoſe him to prefer his carnall intereſts, when they ſtand in competition with Religion; and to aſſay the jumbling together and blending of heaven and earth, rather than he will not attain his ſelf-ends.</p>
                     <p>Suppoſe alſo that there is no humane Law to controule him: I doubt not but in this caſe the Law of God warranteth the taking up of Arms againſt him. My reaſons are theſe which follow:</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Becauſe God hath no where throughout the ſcripture for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118326:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>us to reſiſt ſuch rulers as are a terror to good works. There is no ſin which is not prohibited in the ſcripture.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Becauſe every believer hath, and every man ought to have a propriety in true Religion. Who will dare to deny that the great Senate-houſe of heaven can give a propriety, as effectually as any Parliament upon earth? The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had nothing beſides the great Seal of heaven, to juſtifie their driving out of the <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> from the Land which they had in poſſeſſion, and that was ſufficient, <hi>Iud.</hi> 11.24. Every man hath as firm a Commiſſion to diſpoſſeſs his ſpirituall enemies, and to worſhip God in ſincerity truth.</p>
                     <p>And all who have effected this, have a propriety in true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the exerciſe thereof; and may Lawfully reſiſt all thoſe who go about to reſtrain them from the free uſe of it.</p>
                     <p>The ſixt word in the Decalogue taketh care for the preſervation of mans life, is an hedge about his bodie to reſtrain the incurſions of the Sons of violence; which none can break thorough, but he ſhall get a prick in his Conſcience, and (that I may allude to what the Apoſtle ſpeaketh in another ſence) <hi>pierce thorough his ſoul with many ſorrowes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It forbiddeth men to take away the life, to hinder the health, and ſtrength, and to haſten the death of themſelves, or other men, unleſs for the executing of a judiciarie ſentence: and requireth all men to preſerve other mens lives, but their own in the firſt place, unleſs they can lay them out with advantage to Gods honor: as by fighting his Battels, and helping him againſt his Enemies; or by ſuffering for a good cauſe, when they are not at all likely to defend themſelves by action; or by way of exchange (if an opportuniy be offered) for the life or lives of ſome other, who can do God better ſervice. By virtue of this precept a man is bound in conſcience to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his life if he be able, againſt all malicious plots by w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>. it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermined, and unjuſt practices by which it is aſſaulted: and if he fail herein, he is in the conſpiracie againſt himſelf, acceſſory to his own death, guilty of ſelf-murder.</p>
                     <p>In like manner by the 8th. Commandement we are not only for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to invade that to which we have no right, but enjoyned alſo to preſerve and defend our own livelyhoods from Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, from all who would unjuſtly ſnatch them from us.</p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:118326:14"/>
                     <p>Every man is an Iland, or a little world; and hath ſomewhat which he may call his own, and which he not only lawfully may, but alſo out of duty to God ought to defend from acts of violence according to his abilities, againſt all other men in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.<note n="*" place="margin">We are au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriſed by the Law or Nature to oppoſe force againſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. See <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidore O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>g.</hi> l. 5. <hi>Cicero</hi> in orat. <hi>pro Milone. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Satyr.</hi> 15. <hi>Livie</hi> lib. 42.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That War is juſt</hi> (as a politick writer ſaith well, though in ſome other points he miſcary) <hi>that is neceſſary; and thoſe arms are religious, when there is no hope left elſewhere, but in them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Object.</hi> Some will here Object, that I open a gap to ſedition and tumults; many being apt without due occaſion to pick quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels againſt thoſe whom God hath placed in lawfull authority over them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> Such a determination as I have given of the queſtion which is the ſubject of this chapter, cannot ſmile upon ſedition, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage it; as permitting men to make forcible reſiſtance againſt ſuperiours, only upon juſt occaſions, and when they cannot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a redreſs by ordinary proceedings. That in this ſentence I am orthodox, a learned and juditious author<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Camero</hi> in his Myrothec. Evang. upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15.</note> will bear me witneſs in theſe words which follow.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hoc non eſt ſeditioni in urbe vel caſtris favere, quod civis ultra &amp; injuſſus in rebellem &amp; proditorem Magiſtratum, miles in perduellem Centurionem vel Decurionem ſuum inſurgit, ſi nulla alia via &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione occurrit malo poteſt, tum duntaxat pervertitur ordo &amp; reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>quum extra hujuſmodi caſum tantum quis ſibi permittit &amp; licere putat.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I ſo far expreſſed the ſence of theſe words, in what I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready anſwered to the objection, that I ſhall not need to conſtrue them.</p>
                     <p>But moreover, if any ſhall ſuck poyſon from thoſe truthes, whence they might gather honey, were they of well tempred ſpirits; they will be ſomewhat reſtrained by the diſadvantage up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they ſhould engage againſt thoſe who are poſſeſſed of authority, and by their want of divine aſſiſtance in an unlawfull enterpriſe. And if any ſhall be ſo fool-hardy, and fondly reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, as to engage againſt God and man, againſt Law and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and againſt their own ſafety; let us rather truſt God for the backing of his vice-gerents here upon earth ſo long as they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118326:14"/>themſelves to him, than make a lye our refuge. And though God may ſometimes ſeem to ſleep and not appear in his own cauſe, to wit, when due authority is oppoſed upon empty pretences, <hi>(Talera veritatem, licit amara ſit)</hi> pick not quarrels with truth, becauſe it is bitter, being wreſted by miſ application to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſelfiſh deſignes, and unjuſt proceedings.</p>
                     <p>What I have hitherto ſpoken touching the lawfulneſs of reſiſting Princes upon the occaſion now mentioned, is plentifully confirmed by ſome examples in Scripture; and by the demenours of the <hi>Iews</hi> towards thoſe who reigned over them without Gods immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate appointment; and likewiſe by the practices of Chriſtians. I ſhall premiſe, that if it be lawfull fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> one ſubject, or for one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable number to reſiſt a Prince, then much more for a whole ſtate.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>David</hi> ſhould have troubled God with a needleſs and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent queſtion, asking whether the men of <hi>Keilah</hi> would deliver him up into <hi>Sauls</hi> hand? unleſs he intended there to ſecure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from <hi>Sauls</hi> miſchievous practices; and to offend him rather than not to defend himſelf. <hi>Saul</hi> and his men might eaſily have ſealled the walls of <hi>Keilah,</hi> ſhould <hi>David</hi> have uſed no reſiſtance: and in caſe he had reſiſted <hi>Sauls</hi> force, an arrow or a ſtone would have made no diſtinction between <hi>Saul</hi> and his men.</p>
                     <p>Did not <hi>Azariah</hi> the Prieſt think it lawfull to reſiſt King <hi>Uzzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> in the defence of the Ceremoniall Law,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Chron. 26.17.</note> when he followed him into the Temple, attended with no fewer then 80 Prieſts, and thoſe valiant men? Were not the 80 Prieſts, which accompanied <hi>Uzziah,</hi> of the ſame ſenſe and judgement?</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Iewes</hi> themſelves by their demeanors towards <hi>Alexander Iannaeus,</hi> (who together with his Predeceſſor, and thoſe who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him, are in the <hi>Talmud</hi> called Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe they were not of the Family of <hi>David</hi>) declare that they thought it lawfull for them not only to depoſe, but alſo to inflict capitall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment upon thoſe who reigned over them without Gods imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate appointment.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Alexander Iannaeus</hi> was King over the <hi>Iewes, Ioſeph. Antiq. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daic.</hi> l. 13. c. 20. <hi>Gem. Sanhed.</hi> c. 2. He was convented by the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim, Gem. Sanhed.</hi> c. 2.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Iewes</hi> raiſed warre againſt him, neither would be ſatisfied
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118326:15"/>with any terms without his death; <hi>Ioſeph. Antiq. Iudaic.</hi> l. 13. c. 21, &amp; 22.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Schammai</hi> rebuked the reſt of the <hi>Sanhedrin,</hi> and King <hi>Hirea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> ſhewing favour to <hi>Herod, Ioſeph. Antiq. Iudaic.</hi> lib. 14. cap. 17.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall now briefly explain, how Gods people in the younger times of Chriſtian Religion, by their practices teſtified that they thought it lawfull to reſiſt thoſe who were in authority over them, when they went about to deſtroy, or to deprave Religion, or to impedite the advancement thereof.</p>
                     <p>Whereas the Chriſtians in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who beleeved that the Son was con-ſubſtantiall to the Father, after the death of <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> their Biſhop, made choice of one to ſucceed him, who had been his Predeceſſor, but was ejected by a Council, which the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour convocated to that purpoſe, <hi>Paul</hi> by name; but the <hi>Arians</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> at the ſame time elected <hi>Macedonius</hi> into the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkſhip;<note n="*" place="margin">Socrat. Hiſt Eccleſ. l. 2. c. 12.</note> And <hi>Conſtantius</hi> ſent <hi>Hermogenes,</hi> with a military force to expell <hi>Paul</hi> from the Church of <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> ſome who adhered to <hi>Paul,</hi> fired the houſe in which <hi>Hermogenes</hi> quartered, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him out, ſlew him. <hi>Socrat. Hiſt. Eccleſ.</hi> l. 2. c. 13. <hi>Sozomen. Hist. Eccleſ.</hi> l. 3. c. 6.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Conſtantinopolitans</hi> endeavoured to defend <hi>Paul</hi> their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triark aforenamed againſt <hi>Philip</hi> Preſident of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> when they ſuſpected ſomthing to be decreed againſt him by their Emperor <hi>Conſtantius. Socrat. Hiſt. Eccleſ.</hi> l. 2. c. 16.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> by violence ejecting <hi>Felix</hi> out of the See of <hi>Rome, Conſtantius</hi> againſt his mind reſtoreth unto them <hi>Liberius,</hi> whom he had baniſhed. <hi>Socrat. Hiſt. Eccleſ.</hi> l. 2. c. 37.</p>
                     <p>The Inhabitants of <hi>Mantinium</hi> out of their fervent zeal for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, reſiſted four troops of Soldiers which were ſent againſt them according to the Emperors order, and were victorious. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. Hiſt. Eccleſ.</hi> l. 2. c. 38.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Samoſateans</hi> would by force have attempted to preſerve their Biſhop <hi>Euſebius</hi> from baniſhment, to which <hi>Valens</hi> their Emperour had deſtinated him; had they not been diſwaded by the ſame <hi>Euſebius. Theodorit. Hiſt. Eccleſ.</hi> l. 4. c. 13.</p>
                     <p>The Chriſtians of <hi>Alexandria</hi> reſiſted the Emperour <hi>Martian,</hi> and his military force, <hi>Evagrius Hiſt. Eccleſ.</hi> l. 2. c. 5.</p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118326:15"/>
                     <p>It is ſufficiently known, how <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Millain</hi> oppoſed the Emperor. See <hi>Niceph. Caliſtius</hi> l. 12. c. 42.</p>
                     <p>It is obſervable that the Chriſtians whom I have now mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, when <hi>omnia Caeſar erat,</hi> and whilſt the profeſſion of Chriſtian Religion was confirmed by no humane lawes but the Edicts of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours; in the behalf of Religion reſiſted thoſe who had the <hi>Poſſe</hi> of the world in their hands.</p>
                     <p>That in the elder times of Chriſtian Religion the Papiſts, and likewiſe many Proteſtants of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> have appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved theſe practices of the primitive Chriſtans, and other of higher oppoſition againſt Princes, for default in Government, whether reſpecting Religion, or civill affairs; is ſufficiently diſcovered by <hi>Lyſimachus Nicanor,</hi> in his Epiſtle congratulatory to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters in <hi>Scotland.</hi> See eſpecially, p. 12. 40. 41. 54.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>— Ridentem dicere verum,</l>
                        <l>Quid vetat?</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>The ſenſe of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Senators touching the liableneſs of Kings to forcible reſiſtance and depoſition, is ſo clear from that Vote in the beginning of our Civill diſſentions, to wit, <hi>That the King, if he raiſed Forces againſt his Parliament, forfeited his Truſt;</hi> and by ſome other Votes and Actions, that it needeth no Comment to explain it.</p>
                     <p>He that deſireth to read more touching the Peoples Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in point of reſiſtance to be made againſt thoſe that invade their right, may ſee <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the Lives of the <hi>Gracehi.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:118326:16"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 11.</hi> Kings may render themſelves obnoxious to the penalty of death ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of God, in ſome caſes to be inflicted by publick authority, in other by private men.</head>
                     <p>THat Law, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Whoſe ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed;</hi> reacheth all the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> Princes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, though they be taller than their Brethren by the head and ſhoulders.</p>
                     <p>Whoſo ſheddeth mans blood voluntarily and of his own accord, not out of an error, nor as an executioner of a penaltie, nor yet in his own defence, his blood ſhall be ſhed<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Oakelos</hi> his Chaldee Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe, and the Mauritani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Jewes Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick tranſlation ſet out by <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penius.</hi>
                        </note> by a judiciary ſentence. This is the meaning of that Law.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors have ſome gloſſes here which deſtroy the Text. According to ſome of them, he who by himſelf ſhedded mans blood, was to be puniſhed with death: but if he hired ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or imployed his ſervants to ſhed blood, or expoſed one bound, to a Lion, or other ſavage beaſts, he was to be eſteemed an homicide, and deſerved death to be inflicted of God; but was not neceſſarily to be adjudged to death by the ſentence of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</p>
                     <p>They leave to the King, and likewiſe to the Sanhedrin, a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to puniſh ſuch with death, or to exempt them.</p>
                     <p>Certainly he who committeth murder by a proxie, is more guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty than if he had ſhed blood immediately, in that he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated the ſin.</p>
                     <p>Some of them determine, that, if an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> ſlew a ſtranger (though he was <hi>proſelytus domicilis</hi>) he was not to be condemned to death for it, becauſe he was not (<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>) his neighbour.</p>
                     <p>Theſe conſidered not that ſtrangers alſo bear the Image of God; and that God was the Lord of all mankind.</p>
                     <p>The<note n="*" place="margin">Sanheds. c. 9.</note> 
                        <hi>Miſna</hi> of the <hi>Talmud</hi> telleth us, that when a homicide is mingled with others, they are all free, that is (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) when many men ſtrike a man ſo that it cannot be known that what was done by any one of them, killed him.</p>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:118326:16"/>
                     <p>This exception hath no more warrant from the word of God than have the two former.</p>
                     <p>Who ſo ſheddeth mans blood, whether by himſelf immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, or by the miniſtery of ſome other, whether a ſtrangers or a neighbours; whether alone or with the help of others, is a ſon of death.</p>
                     <p>No Mortall is excuſed by his greatneſs. <hi>Plato</hi> is very orthodox in this point.<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. And ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micide, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. He urgeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the in flicting of this penalty, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially upon ſuch as ſhall kill any of their kindred.</note> An homicide (as he determineth l. 9 <hi>de leg.</hi>) muſt be puniſhed with death.</p>
                     <p>He paſſeth the ſame ſentence upon a Sranger killing a Stranger, and a Citizen killing a Stranger, and a Stranger killing a Citizen, as upon one Citizen killing another, and upon a man killing ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his own hand, or otherwiſe. He excepteth not any ſo offending from capitall puniſhment.</p>
                     <p>That it is not left arbitrary to the Magiſtrate to puniſh or pardon Murther, is cleared by the 33. Section of <hi>Num.</hi> 35. where it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that <hi>The Land cannot be clear ſed from the blood that is ſhed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but by the blood of him that ſhed it.</hi> Vpon which place ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">More Nevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim, Part. 3. cap. 41.</note> 
                        <hi>Maimonides,</hi> (as he is conſtrued by <hi>Buxtorf</hi> agreeably to the ſence of the <hi>Hebrew.</hi>) <hi>Proptereà licet interfectus per horas vel dies aliquot adhuc vixerit, locutus fuerit, ſanumque intellectum retinue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, teſtatuſque fuerit, ſe ei condonare &amp; remittere, non auditur, ſed neceſſariò anima pro animâ danda eſt, aequaliter pro parvo &amp; magno, ſervo &amp;</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">F lio ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum, <hi>ſeu filio nobilium.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>libero, ſapiente &amp; ſtulto.</hi> Take notice from this gloſs, that the murderer ought neceſſarily to be put to death, though the perſon murdered live ſome days after he receive the wound: which is contrary to the ſenſe of ſome other <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors.</p>
                     <p>God in divers places of Scripture requireth that capitall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be inflicted, as for murder ſo for ſome other crimes: neither are Kings excepted from thoſe Laws in any part of the written word which is now extant.</p>
                     <p>Princes in ſome other caſes are liable to capitall puniſhment to be inflicted by private men.</p>
                     <p>When a Prince attempteth to murder another, the perſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded may lawfully kill him in his own defence, and is bound by the 6. Commandement to doe it, rather than ſuffer himſelf to be murdered. <hi>Davids</hi> great guard intimateth, that he would
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118326:17"/>rather have killed <hi>Saul,</hi> than have ſuffered himſelf to be killed by him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. <hi>9</hi> de leg.</note>
                        <hi>Plato</hi> maketh it lawfull for a man to kill a Thief who by night entereth his houſe to ſteal;<note n="*" place="margin">That is, when he purſaeth a young woman betrothed, to defile her, ſaith <hi>R. Schem. Tof.</hi> The wifes n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs is the husbands na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs: but <hi>Maimonides</hi> his words are more compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive, than that Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter maketh them. That place in <hi>Plato's Lawes,</hi> before quoted, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for the chaſtity of both Sexes, whether mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edor ſingle: <hi>Maimonides</hi> his words are capable of the ſame conſtiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; <hi>adam</hi> ſometimes being of as large a Signification, as <hi>bomo.</hi> That teſtimony which have added out of the <hi>Miſua,</hi> prevaileth with me to think, that <hi>Maimonid.</hi> under <hi>adam</hi> compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended both Sexes.</note> or one that attempteth at any time after what manner ſoever to ſpoil him of his goods; or one who invadeth his chaſtitie, or hath defiled ſome other related to him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Maimonides</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is unlawfull to kill a man who hath purpoſed to commit any wickedneſs, before he hath done it, unleſſe in theſe</hi> 2 <hi>caſes,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>when he purſueth a man to kill him, and when he purſueth a mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs to uncover it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Miſna</hi> in <hi>Sanbedr.</hi> c. 8. paragr. 7. to the ſame purpoſe <hi>Theſe are they whom they hinder</hi> from ſinne <hi>by the loſs of their life: him that purſueth another with an intention to kill him, and him that purſueth a maid, and him that puſueth a young woman that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Should one purſue another to kill him, all <hi>Iſrael</hi> (according to the ſenſe of our <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors) was bound to reſcue the perſon who was purſued, if it could not be effected otherwiſe, by the death of the purſuer.</p>
                     <p>Should any one deliver an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> or his goods into the power of the Heathen, it was lawfull (ſay<note n="*" place="bottom">
                           <hi>See</hi> Maimonid. <hi>and</hi> Moſes Mikotſi, <hi>quoted by Mr.</hi> Selden De Jur. Natur. &amp; Gent. juxta Diſcipl. Hebr. <hi>li. 4. c. 3.</hi>
                        </note> the ſame Writers) for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one to kill the Traytor. It is as great a fault to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the goods and lives of Chriſtians into the hands of Papiſts.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118326:17"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 12.</hi> The injunction of ſubjection to the higher powers, is but a brittle Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for the impunity of Tyrants.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>CHryſoſtome</hi> taketh notice that the Apoſtle [<hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.] <hi>doth not ſay, there is no ruler but of God; but that he ſpake of the office, ſaying, there is no power but of God; all the powers that be are ordained of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>According to this Doctor, the ſcope of the Apoſtle is not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit men from reſiſting Tyrants, but to bridle-in unruly ſpirits, which are altogether impatient of any authority.</p>
                     <p>I may adde, that this Scripture likewiſe oppoſeth thoſe who could be contented to ſubmit unto ſuch Magiſtrates, as will countenance their licentious courſes, but cannot endure ſuch as goe about to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain ſin, and to encourage religion.</p>
                     <p>If by <hi>powers</hi> be meant, <hi>ſuch as are inveſted in authority;</hi> the trope uſed will chaſtiſe all ſuch as reſiſt Magiſtrates who are duely called to the exerciſe of authority, neither abuſe the authority wherewith they are betruſted; and ſo diſcover themſelves to be enemies to authority it ſelf: but the peoples hands are not tyed, when authority is uſurped, or the ends thereof neglected.</p>
                     <p>What we read <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. according to Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Buchanan,</hi> bindeth us onely to ſubmit our ſelves to the Edicts of Princes, when they enjoyn us what is agreeable to the Law of God. And indeed the reaſons which inforce our ſubjection to the higher powers, and the motives which incite us to our dutie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in 3. and 4. verſes of the Chapter before quoted, byaſe us into that ſenſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>For rulers are not a terrour to good works, but to the evill.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>We muſt be ſubject to rulers, becauſe they are not a terror to good works: and becauſe they are a terror to the evill.</p>
                     <p>We have afterward a double motive to the ſubjection which is enjoyned us. <hi>Doe that which is good, and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the power. But if thou doe that which is evill, be afraid: for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate beareth not the ſword in vain: for he is the miniſter of God, a revenger to execute wrath upon him that doth evill.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:118326:18"/>
                     <p>That injunction (<hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.) cannot pretend to bind us to the obſervance of the Magiſtrate, when he is a terror to good works, but not to evill: when thoſe who doe evill, have praiſe of him; and thoſe who doe good, are diſcountenanced, and puniſhed by him.</p>
                     <p>The reaſons of a Law, whether divine, or humane, are the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the latitude of it. Civil Courts of Equity are appointed to exempt us from the literall ſeverity of humane Lawes, where it is not accompanied with the reaſons thereof.</p>
                     <p>The Holie Ghoſt (as we ſee) in the Scripture exhibited requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſubjection to be given onely to thoſe who are legitimately called to the exerciſe of government; and to ſuch onely ſo long as they rule well. Tyrannie is not ordained of God, nor ſupported by the other reaſons for which ſubjection is enjoyned, or by the motives thereunto, before mentioned.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Beza</hi> underſtandeth by the <hi>higher powers,</hi> both the ſupreme and inferiour Magiſtrates.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Buchanan</hi> conceiveth that we are no more tied to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Kings, then to inferiour Officers, by vertue of that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                     <p>The Author of the Appoſtolicall Conſtitutions (l. 7. c. 17.) in the Latine interpreter's judgment expreſſeth the ſame ſenſe. His words are theſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Thou ſhalt fear the King, knowing that the choice is of the Lord: thou ſhalt honour his Magistrates, as the Miniſters of God, for they are the revengers of all iniquity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Latine interpreter in the Margent directeth us to <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and the word uſed by the Author of the <hi>Apoſtolicall Conſtitutions,</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3. not <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, as the 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. I doubt not but in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3. the ſupreme and ſubordinate rulers are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to be underſtood.</p>
                     <p>The reaſons which back the authority of Rulers, make alike for both. <hi>Peter</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle c. 2.13, 14. preſſeth upon us alike ſubmiſſion to the ſupreme Magiſtrate, and to ſubordinate Rulers. To this Scripture (I think) the Author of the Apoſtolicall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions alludeth in the place before quoted.</p>
                     <p>Scarce any will deny, but a man in ſome caſes may reſiſt, and likewiſe kill an inferiour Magiſtrate without offence to God. Who
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118326:18"/>will doubt, ſhould a Conſtable rob upon the High-way, but a traveller upon whom he maketh an onſet, may lawfully, if it be neceſſary to the defence of his own life, or of his goods, make op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the utmoſt of his ability?</p>
                     <p>If any diſtinguiſh between ſuch an one's perſon and his Office, I anſwer, that the ſame diſtinction may be applied to the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as well as to his miniſters. There is a vaſt diſtance between the oppoſing of authority, and the reſiſting of the perſon inveſted therein, who abuſeth it, or otherwiſe miſdemeaneth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quest.</hi> Some will be ready here to aske, whether the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were not bound in Conſcience to be ſubject unto the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Emperours, though they were Heathens, and Tyrants; ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling according to their own wills, and not called to the exerciſe of Authority by Gods immediate choice, nor yet by the Choice of the Major part of the people.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> I conceive (but with ſubmiſſion to better judgments) that thoſe Chriſtians who lived under the Heatheniſh Emperours, but wanted ſtrength to defend themſelves, were by that precept, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject unto the higher powers,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to ſit ſtill, and to endeavour nothing againſt thoſe who had the ſword in their hands. My reaſon is this (but the cauſe depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not upon it) The Holy Ghoſt there injoyneth not only a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obedience, but alſo ſuch a temperament of ſpirit, as is patient of lawfull Government, and cheerfully ready to ſubmit unto it; of which thoſe fall ſhort who forcibly reſiſt unlawfull Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; when in all probability the oppoſition which they make, will only exaſperate and not diſpell the evill which they groan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Thoſe who in ſuch circumſtances uſe reſiſtance, diſcover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be of unruly ſpirits: (which frame of mind is forbidden) in that they proceed wholly according to paſſion; and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the dictate of a ſober and well-ordered judgment. But the injunction according to the immediate ſenſe of it, requireth only ſubjection unto the powers which are ordained of God: and I know not with what ſpectacles any one can diſcern tyranny to be of that number.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Children</hi> (ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Enchicid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e. <hi>37.</hi>
                        </note> Epictetus) <hi>muſt yield to a Father in all things, and when he revileth or ſtriketh them, muſt patiently bear it, becauſe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118326:19"/>by Nature they ſtand related to a Father, as a Father, not to a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as good.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Subjects are not ſo rigorouſly tyed to ſubmit to their Prince, in that their engagement is not naturall but adventitious.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 13.</hi> The <hi>15</hi> Section of Pſalm <hi>105.</hi> vindicated from miſ-interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
                     <p>THat negative precept, <hi>Touch not mine Anointed, and doe my Prophets no harm,</hi> if rightly underſtood, will not contradict thoſe <hi>Theſes</hi> which I before propounded.</p>
                     <p>That Scripture conceiveth that we cannot without ſin offer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie to the Lords Anointed. This is the mind of it.</p>
                     <p>It pointeth at <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> as we may gather from the context, compared with the Hiſtory of their lives. God reproved <hi>Pharaoh</hi> for <hi>Abram's</hi> ſake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.17. And <hi>Abimelech</hi> for <hi>Abraham's</hi> ſake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.3. God reſtrained <hi>Abimelech</hi> from hurting <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 26. God reproved <hi>Laban</hi> for <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.24.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>R. Alſheach</hi> upon that comma of the Pſalmiſt before quoted, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth us that <hi>Laban</hi> was King of <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> and that he was <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhan-Riſhathaim.</hi> He with ſome other who affirm the ſame, had no reaſon to conceive that <hi>Laban</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Cuſhan-Riſhathaim,</hi> who is mentioned <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3. nor more ground to think that <hi>Laban</hi> had that name. But thoſe who were wealthy, eſpecially if they had great families, had the name of Princes. The children of <hi>Heth</hi> called <hi>Abraham</hi> a mighty Prince, <hi>Gen.</hi> 23.6.</p>
                     <p>It's as eaſie a matter to make good that <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> were the Lords Anointed, as that God reproved Kings for their ſakes.</p>
                     <p>I cannot cloſe with thoſe <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors, who tell us that the whole world ſet <hi>Abraham</hi> a King over them, but ſhall ſhew that in ſeverall reſpects, he, with <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> might fitly be called the Lords Anointed.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. There is an Anointing with the Spirit, ſealing to our hearts
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118326:19"/>the promiſes of God, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21.) in which they had a large portion.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. They were Anointed with the Spirit of Illumination and of Holineſſe, and ſo became Prophets, and Kings and Prieſts unto their God. Every true beleever hath his conſcience ſo illuminated, that he is a Prophet to himſelf, and is ſo ſanctified that he hath victorie and dominion over his luſts, and offereth up himſelf a living ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to God. See 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10, 11. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. All thoſe three Worthies before-named were Prophets, as ſome of our <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors have obſerved.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Abrah<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m</hi> is expreſly called a Prophet, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Iſaac</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied in the benedictions which he gave to his Sons, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. And <hi>Iacob</hi> propheſied <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.</p>
                     <p>This Expoſition is very well acquainted with that Text of the Pſalmiſt. The end of the Verſe commenteth upon the beginning, and telleth us in what ſenſe they were called the Lords Anointed. See <hi>Ger.</hi> 20.7.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aben-Ezra</hi> upon Pſal. 105.15. conſtrueth the word <hi>Anointed</hi> into a double ſenſe, viz. <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> but the ſame Scholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſt upon <hi>Gen.</hi> 23.6. ſaith that <hi>Abraham</hi> was called a <hi>Prince of God,</hi> becauſe, he was a Prophet. As he was a Prophet, he was lifted up into a degree of dignity above thoſe who were not Prophets, as the word which is tranſlated a <hi>Prince,</hi> importeth. And ſo I conceive with <hi>Onkelos,</hi> that he is there ſignified to be a <hi>Prince before the Lord,</hi> rather then a <hi>great Prince,</hi> although he was truly great, becauſe he was ſo highly honoured of God. In the ſame notion the Prieſts are called <hi>Princes of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.5. And <hi>Rachels</hi> prayers for Children, the <hi>wreſtlings of God, Gen.</hi> 30.8. But by the <hi>mountains of God,</hi> Pſal. 36.7. are meant <hi>great mountains,</hi> and by the <hi>Cedars of God,</hi> Pſal. 80.11. <hi>tall Cedars;</hi> The <hi>flame of God,</hi> Cantic. 8, 6. is a <hi>moſt vehement flame.</hi> In this Scripture the <hi>Hebrew</hi> for God, is <hi>Iah,</hi> in thoſe two places in the Pſalms, <hi>El,</hi> in the other three places quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Elohim,</hi> (Gods.) Strength or greatnes is an eſſential attribute of God, but the Prophets and Prieſts were dignified by and in the preſence of the three ſacred perſons, and <hi>Rachel</hi> powred out her prayers before the bleſſed Trinity.</p>
                     <p>It is competently clear from what I have ſaid upon Pſal. 105.15.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118326:20"/>that by Gods Anointed there are meant ſuch as were not Kings, but over their own Families; and that thoſe who were command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to hurt them, neither to doe them harm, were not in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to them; and the matter of the Commandement is, that they ſhould offer them no wrrong.</p>
                     <p>The ſtrength of this precept doth not ſo tie the hands of Princes, but that they have liberty upon ſome occaſions to make War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt other Princes who are without the circumference of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and endeavour to ſubdue them; nor yet ſo confine Subjects, that they may not lawfully defend their right againſt their Princes.</p>
                     <p>I acknowledge that men are by the impetuouſnes of a native diſtemper, till ſuch time as it be reſtrained and bridled by grace, carried on to envie ſuch as God hath placed in authority over them. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> becauſe they were highly in favour with God, were envied and hated by a great party of the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites.</hi> Farre be it from me to countenance this Anarchicall humor. We ſin, if we withdraw from any, whilſt they have lawfull autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over us, and rule well, our due ſubjection: yet I ſee not that they are ſo baracadoed by the Law of God againſt all oppoſition, that it ſhould be unlawfull upon any occaſion whatſoever to reſiſt, or to queſtion them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. <hi>14.</hi> An Argument, which is wont to be drawn from <hi>1. Sam. 24.6.</hi> and <hi>c. 26.9, 10, 11.</hi> is propounded.</head>
                     <p>THe main pillar by which Tyranny is ſupported remaineth ſtill unſhaken, <hi>viz. Davids</hi> Authority or teſtimony for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfullneſs of killing <hi>Saul,</hi> when God had delivered him up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hands, which is expreſſed, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.6. c. 26.9, 10, 11.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And he ſaid unto his Men</hi> (in the former of theſe Scriptures) <hi>the Lord forbid that I ſhould do this thing unto my Maſter the Lords anointed to ſtretch forth my hand againſt him, ſeeing he is the Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And</hi> David <hi>ſaid to</hi> Abiſhai (in the other place quoted) <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118326:20"/>him not: for who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed and be guiltleſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>David <hi>ſaid further more, as the Lord liveth, the Lord ſhall ſmite him, or his day ſhall come to dye, or he ſhall deſcend into Battail and periſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Lord forbid that I ſhould ſtretch forth mine hand againſt the Lords Anointed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Many now a days in their familiar diſcourſes allege for <hi>Tyrants</hi> immunity from cenſures, eſpecially from depoſition and capitall puniſhment, the example of <hi>Saul</hi> and his ſucceſſors in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
                     <p>This their argument ſhould ſcarce have any ſhew of a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Saul,</hi> ſhould have in regard of him no firmer baſis then a Caſtle in the air, were they not beholden to the text that I have now quoted.</p>
                     <p>Whereas God requireth that thoſe who have committed mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. Compare alſo the 6 Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement with the ſcope of it.</note> be put to death<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. <hi>13.</hi>
                        </note> by the Magiſtrate: and hath made it<note n="*" place="margin">Compare the 6. Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement with the ſcope of it.</note> a mans duty to kill another if he can, rather than to ſuffer himſelf to be murthered.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>David</hi> ſeemeth to except all violence which is offered by tyrants, even that which amounteth to the endangering of other mens lives, from ſuch rough and auſtere replies, and to leave unto their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects (or rather their vaſſals) no weapons but prayers and tears, flight and lurking holes wherewith to defend themſelves.</p>
                     <p>This Argument though nothing ſhould be added to its ſtature, would prove the <hi>Goliah</hi> of thoſe who love to diſpute them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into ſlavery, or elſe to ſhare with Tyrants in their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; but is ſomewhat heightned and ſtrengthned by ſome cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in Which <hi>David</hi> ſtood, <hi>viz.</hi> his frequent dangers in regard of <hi>Saul,</hi> (by whom he was reſtleſly purſued) and the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his own perſon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>David,</hi> leſt <hi>Abiſhai</hi> ſhould have conceived that although it was unlawfull for a private man to ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords anointed, yet one anointed might ſtretch forth his hand againſt another, after he had ſaid<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9.</note> 
                        <hi>Who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords Anointed, and be gniltleſs?</hi> addeth, <hi>The Lord forbid that I ſhould ſtretch forth my hand againſt the Lords Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> ſaith <hi>Abarbinel</hi> upon the place, He intimateth, that it was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118326:21"/>obvious to think, that although it was a fault in ſome one to ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords Anointed, yet not in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> who was himſelf alſo the anointed of the Lord.</p>
                     <p>That <hi>David</hi> ſhould cauſe the <hi>Amalekite</hi> to be put to death, who witneſſed againſt himſelf that he had ſlain <hi>Saul,</hi> contributeth no more to the preſerving of the lives of Kings then of other men, in that the party who accuſed himſelf could not pretend to any authority by which he might adjudge <hi>Saul</hi> to death, nor yet plead that he ſlew him in his own defence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 15.</hi> One of the premiſes from which ſome conclude that all Kings are by divine right exempted from legall cenſures, and forcible reſiſtance, is convicted of falſitie.</head>
                     <p>IT is taken for granted in the argument which is founded upon thoſe places in <hi>Samuel</hi> which were produced in the laſt Chapter, that there is as good reaſon that all other Kings as that <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould be exempted from humane cenſures and forcible reſiſtance, which ſuppoſition I ſhall acknowledge to be <hi>Truths</hi> legitimate off-ſpring, and Aeagle-like to ſore above the miſts and clouds of ignorance and falſhood, if it can with an undazled and undaunted eye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Sun of reaſon. But you ſhall clearly perceive it to blink, when it is brought to the tryall.</p>
                     <p>There are many reaſons ſure, for which <hi>Saul</hi> being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with other Kings, had a large advantage in the caſes now mentioned.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Becauſe he reigned by Gods immediate appointment. God made choice of <hi>Saul</hi> to be Captain over his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.16, 17.</p>
                     <p>Thoſe Kings who were choſen and autorized immediately by God, had a vaſt advantage, being compared with ſuch as ſhould be choſen by men. When God ſuſpended the people from the act of Electing, he ſuſpended them alſo from the act of Depoſing, otherwiſe they might preſently have pulled down him whom God had ſet up.</p>
                     <p>I acknowledge a difference between the prohibiting people from
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118326:21"/>depoſing a Prince (enthroned immediately by God himſelf) <hi>quam diu benè ſe geſſerit,</hi> ſo long as he demeaned himſelf as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a prince, and an abſolute debarring of them from going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to alter their condition, howſoever ſuch a Prince ſhould carry himſelf.</p>
                     <p>A King by his mandate giving one title to ſome place in a ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that have Lawes by which they are enabled (unleſs a ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiour power interpoſe) to eject any member of their corporation for certain miſdemeanours, or becauſe they retain not thoſe qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications which are required in a member of ſuch a body (though permitted otherwiſe both by the Laws of God and men) is not wont to reſerve the party whom he hath preferred, to his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate juriſdiction, but leaveth him to ſtand or fall by the ſtatutes of the ſociety into which he is admitted.</p>
                     <p>But neither may I omit a difference between the ſupreme Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and earthly Monarches in this particular. So boundleſs are the knowledg and power of God, that he ſees all the Delinquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the great ones, and can puniſh them immediately by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf without any interruption of his affairs.</p>
                     <p>That God, whoſe breath like a ſtream of Brimſtone kindleth Tophet, ſtandeth not in need of any inſtruments for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his wrath upon Kings, and ſometimes himſelf immediately inflicteth vengeance, ſometimes is pleaſed to aſſign unto men that office out of the ſovereignty of his will.</p>
                     <p>What we read, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.20. leaveth us doubtfull, whether God upon any occaſions autoriſed the <hi>Iſraclites</hi> to reject their Kings, or their poſterity. He might out of a diſpleaſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived againſt the King permit his ſubjects or ſtrangers to offer ſuch violence unto him, as he did not approve of. Himſelf like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by a penall ſentence might tranſlate the Kingdom from one Family to another.</p>
                     <p>One of the reaſons which moved <hi>David</hi> to ſwear, <hi>As the Lord liveth, the Lord ſhall ſmite him, or his day ſhall come to dye, or he ſhall deſcend into baettell and periſh,</hi> was, unleſs <hi>Abarbinel</hi> miſconſtrue him, becauſe he knew that the Lord had Anonited him King.</p>
                     <p>Moſt certain it is that <hi>Saul</hi> could not (without injuſtice) be depoſed by humane authority, much leſs ſuffer capitall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118326:22"/>by any humane cenſures, ſo long as he demeaned himſelf ſo as it became him: in which reſpect he had a large advantage being compared with other Kings who were mens creatures, <hi>viz.</hi> not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected immediately by God himſelf, much more above ſuch whoſe ſword is all the title by which they can pretend to the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                     <p>Thoſe are as free, as can be imagined, to recover their liberty, who are enſlaved by conqueſt; an unlawfull violence may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be removed.</p>
                     <p>A people may ſet a King over them for ſome ſhort time, ſo that his autority muſt needs ſoon expire; or with no firmer commiſſion then <hi>durante beneplacito,</hi> ſo that his Kingdom ſhall not be more ſtedfaſt than one of thoſe houſes whoſe foundations are ſaid in the waves, the inhabitants whereof may expect to be toſſed to and fro without intermiſſion, unleſs they can congeale the billowes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſleep.</p>
                     <p>The Authority which is perpetuated by the tenor of the Patent, may in ſome caſes be recalled both with more wiſdom and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then it was granted, as I before ſhewed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 16.</hi> That Preſumption, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is as good reaſon that all other Kings as well as <hi>Saul,</hi> ſhould be exempted from humane cenſures, and violent reſiſtance, is by another reaſon refuted. The Sin of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in asking a King, is explained negatively and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matively. The <hi>14.</hi> and <hi>15.</hi> Verſes of <hi>Deuteron. 17.</hi> are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened.</head>
                     <p>GOD, though he granted unto the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> a King after the manner of other Nations, and according to the <hi>Genius</hi> of their requeſt, might deſervedly abridge them from that libertie of unthroning Tyrants, which he granted unto other Nations: in that they tendered to him ſuch a Petition, as was both in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and the circumſtances thereof exceedingly unlawfull and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. God gave them a King in his anger, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.11.</p>
                     <p>God threatneth by <hi>Samuel</hi> (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.18.) that he would not hear the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> crying out to him for relief under the burden of their royall preſſures.</p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:118326:22"/>
                     <p>This Scripture informeth us that God determined they ſhould ſuffer in the things wherein they ſinned. Here is meaſure for meaſure.</p>
                     <p>That I may explain the ſin of the <hi>Iſra lites</hi> in its full dimenſions, I ſhall premiſe, That a King is not a neceſſary ingredient of the Government of a People, (which <hi>Theſis</hi> I have already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:) Moreover, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were not obliged by any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine precept to ſet over them a King: And laſtly, that although a King had been neceſſary for other Nations in regard of Civill oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, yet could not he be neceſſary for the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were not neceſſitated by any divine precept to ſet over them a King of their own chuſing, nor yet to ask a King of God.</p>
                     <p>Three things (ſaith <hi>R. Jehuda</hi>) were injoyned the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedr. c. 2.</note> which they ſhould doe after their entrance into the Holy Land: to ſet a King over them, to cut off the ſeed of <hi>Amaleck,</hi> and to build a Temple. <hi>Schickard</hi> alſo (<hi>De Jure Regio Hebraeorum,</hi> c. 1. <hi>Theor.</hi> 1.) affirmeth, that God commanded the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to ſet a King over them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.15.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Dei manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>at elige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Regem.</note>The title of that Theoreme is yet more hardie, affirming that God had commanded the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to chuſe them a King.</p>
                     <p>But if we accurately examine that comma in <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Schickard,</hi> we ſhall find that God did not at all permit, much leſs command the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to chuſe a King, but reſerved that choice to himſelf. Neither is there any expreſſion in <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. which might countenance their asking of a King, but clearly what ſhould have diverted them from that attempt.</p>
                     <p>It's probable alſo that thoſe words, <hi>Thou ſhalt in any wiſe ſet him him King over thee, whom the Lord thy God ſhall chuſe,</hi> (conſider well the ſcope of them) contain onely one precept, which is nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, <hi>viz.</hi> That they ſhould not ſet over them a King whom the Lord did not chuſe: and certain, that if an affirmative precept be likewiſe intended in them; the reaſon was not, that God took complacency in their ſetting over them a King, but that his choice might be regarded. Their <hi>acquieſcing in Gods choice</hi> ſhould be the pith and kernel of the precept, and the <hi>ſetting up of a King</hi> onely the husk and ſhell of it. It was needleſs to injoyn them to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118326:23"/>King over them, when they intemperately deſired Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. God did not antecedently, nor ſimply injoyn them to ſet a King over them, but (if at all) in reference to the choice that he ſhould make. And he chuſ'd a King for them, not out of any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placencie which he took in their requeſt, but out of condeſcenſion to the hardneſs of their hearts.</p>
                     <p>Again,<note n="*" place="margin">The Book which <hi>Samue!</hi> wrote touching the manner of the Kingdom, (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.15) ſhewed what autority the K. ſhould have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the people, and what pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment he ſhould inſlict upon thoſe who diſobeyed his commands, and was layed up before the Lord, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Ark, as <hi>R. Levi Bell Gerſom</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth upon the place.</note> though a King ſhould have been neceſſary for other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet not for the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> God had undertaken to rule over them in a more peculiar way then over the Nations, had promiſed to goe before them, and to fight their battles, and had given them Judges, and directed them by his Prophets.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the times of the Iudges before <hi>Samuel,</hi> ſeemed to be of this opinion.</p>
                     <p>This laſt <hi>Theſis</hi> is cleared by 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.19. <hi>And ye have this day rejected your God, who himſelf ſaved you out of all your adverſities, and your tribulations.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in deſiring a King, did not act in the virtue of any divine commandement, nor out of any Civil neceſſity, or State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exigency, but out of an unbridled humor, out of a <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>exie</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill frame of ſpirit. I cannot think with ſome of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors in <hi>Siphre,</hi> that they deſired a King who would bring in Idolatrous worſhip; nor with <hi>R. Niſſim,</hi> that their offence was in asking a King, not only to fight their battails, but alſo to judge them, (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all judicature was not entailed upon their great Sanhedrin and their inferiour judges, it was not neceſſary that their requeſt ſhould encroach upon thoſe Courts of juſtice, which were eſtabliſhed by Divine right) nor yet with ſome other, that their ſin conſiſted in deſiring a King who ſhould make laws and rule according to his pleaſure, not ſubmitting himſelf unto the Law of God, ſeeing that we have no hint that they were guilty of this crime.</p>
                     <p>They offended (as I conceive with <hi>Maimonidas</hi>) in that there was a ſpirit of murmuring in their asking of a King. They were not contented with that Government which God had appointed them. God permitted them not to aske a King, but commanded them to ſet over them a King whom the Lord ſhould choſe. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.14, 15. God foretelleth their repining againſt the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and here, as in ſome other caſes, condeſcendeth to the hardneſs of their hearts in granting them a King, but confineth them to one whom himſelf ſhould chuſe.</p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:118326:23"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>R. Nehorai</hi> (in the <hi>Gemara</hi> of <hi>Sanhedrin</hi> c. 2.) expreſſeth the ſame ſenſe of that place in <hi>Deut. viz.</hi> That in regard of their mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, which is intimated in thoſe words, <hi>And ſhalt ſay, I will ſet a King over me, like as all the Nations that are round about me,</hi> the Lord ſaid, Thou ſhalt in any wiſe ſet him King over thee, whom the Lord thy God ſhall chuſe.</p>
                     <p>Thoſe Doctors, whoſe opinions I rejected, miſtook, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that God abſolutely commanded the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to ſet over them a King; and ſinned not, in the matter of their requeſt, but only in the circumſtances thereof. Had there been ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, their forefathers had ſinned in omitting it, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the time after they were poſseſſed of <hi>Canaan,</hi> till they asked a King.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Nath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manides</hi> upon <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10.</note>They ſinned alſo in rejecting <hi>Samuel,</hi> one who was endewed with the Spirit of prophecie, and eminent in holineſſe. Beſides that they expreſſed a deſire that ſome other ſhould rule over them, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.5. Vnleſſe they were ſupinely ignorant, or underſtood by revelation that God would not ſettle the Kingdom at its begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon <hi>Iudah,</hi> they could no expect a king who was not of that tribe.</p>
                     <p>They had an itching deſire to be like unto other Natations, in w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> there was a ſpice &amp; tincture of Idolatry. They choſe rather to be governed after the manner of the heathen, then in that way which God had preſcribed them, being taken with the pomp and luſtre of a viſible King. As they had formerly adored the Gods of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo now they idolize their government: as they had often caſt off <hi>Iehovah</hi> from being their God, ſo now they caſt him off from being their King.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>R. Eliezer</hi> (in the <hi>Gemara</hi> of <hi>Sanhedr.</hi> c. 2.) ſayth, the Elders ſinned not in asking a King, but the common people were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe in affecting to be like other Nations.</p>
                     <p>The beginnning of this ſentence is already refuted: the remainder in part maketh for my purpoſe. The ſame who deſired a King, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected alſo to be like other Nations, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.5. &amp;. 20. and were therein perverſe, but ſinned likewiſe in the matter of their requeſt. It was impoſſible for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to aske a King with ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances as not to ſin, in that the requeſt it ſelf implied a rejecting of God from bearing rule over them.</p>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:118326:24"/>
                     <p>They had not the ſame liberty with other Nations in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, in that God had vouchſafed to reign over them in a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar manner.</p>
                     <p>Foraſmuch as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſo haynouſly provoked God in asking a King, it was juſt with him to abridge them or the Liberty of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Tyrannicall Kings which he left to other Nations: that they might have enough of Kingly government, which they had ſo much thirſted after.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 17.</hi> A third reaſon is oppoſed against that propoſition, or preſumption, which was examined in the two laſt Chapters.</head>
                     <p>SHould we grant that <hi>Davids</hi> ſparing of <hi>Saul,</hi> when he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered into his hands, was approved off by God, yet the times in which he lived, will ſuggeſt an exception of Tyrants now a dayes from <hi>Sauls</hi> Privilege, and of ſubjects whoſe lives are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly ſought after by their Princes, from <hi>Davids</hi> Liberty.</p>
                     <p>No one will doubt but in the times in which the ſpirit of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie flouriſhed, God diſpenced oftner with the matter of his Laws then we have notice given us in the Scriptures.</p>
                     <p>God remitted unto <hi>Cain</hi> the ſentence of death due to him for his Murder. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.15. That Law, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Who ſo ſheddeth mans blood, By man ſhall his blood be ſhed,</hi> was not then firſt given, but only repeated and inforced by a vocall promulgation. God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the <hi>Iſralites</hi> to ſpoil the <hi>Aegyptians, Exod.</hi> 11.2. And ſome of thoſe of whom they borrowed jewels, perhaps had no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence into their preſſures. If all Gods providential diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould have been written, I ſuppoſe that even the World it ſelf could not contain the Bookes that ſhould be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
                     <p>I cannot conceive that it will ſeem ſtrange to any who are not ſworn to hold their concluſions, that <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould by ſome un-writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten diſpenſation be exempted from ſome penalties, to which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he ſhould have been liable, or that <hi>David</hi> by ſome counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand which was not committed to writing, ſhould be inhibited from killing <hi>Saul,</hi> which otherwiſe he might have done in his own
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118326:24"/>defence:<note n="*" place="margin">Upon 1 Sam. 26.</note> 
                        <hi>Abarbinel</hi> ſaith by way of conjecture, that <hi>David</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from <hi>Samuel</hi> at <hi>Naioth</hi> in <hi>Ramah,</hi> what he ſaith to <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.10. God had promiſed <hi>David</hi> the Kingdom, and ſo vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually at leaſt that he would deliver him out of the hands of <hi>Saul:</hi> and that his information, out of ſuppoſition that he ſinned not in ſparing <hi>Saul,</hi> was ich'd out by ſome divine light not recorded in Scripture, ſith otherwiſe he might have conceived that God had decreed he ſhould by his Sword hew out his way to the Kingdom, that Gods promiſe was to be accompliſhed by his killing of <hi>Saul,</hi> when he was delivered into his hands. It is probable enough, that God by ſome revelation not contained in the Scriptures now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, ſignified unto <hi>David,</hi> that himſelf without his help would ſhorten <hi>Sauls</hi> dayes, and admoniſhed him expreſly, or by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence not to lay violent hands upon his Maſter the Lords anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. I am confident that the Hiſtorie of ſome privileges which were granted to <hi>Saul,</hi> and thoſe who by Gods appointment ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him in the Kingdom, periſhed with that book which <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> wrote concerning the manner of the Kingdom, and layed up before the Lord, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.25.</p>
                     <p>That Book was of divine authority, but not joyned to the other Scriptures, in that it would be of little uſe after the Kingdom ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired: and Gods Providence ordered that thoſe divine Writings which ſhould be tranſmitted to all poſterity, ſhould be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ſuch a volume as would be portable, and might be eaſily purchaſed. When I before ſpake of unwritten diſpenſations and precepts, I meant ſuch as were not inſerted in the Scriptures, which ſhould be preſerved as a perpetuall rule of our lives. And perhaps there was never but for ſome ſhort time, any unwritten tradition, but in this ſenſe.</p>
                     <p>It is is probable enough that the Book of which <hi>Samuel</hi> maketh mention, periſhed with the firſt Temple. The ſacred Writings (as <hi>Elias Levita</hi> witneſſeth) were not gathered into one Volume, till after the <hi>Babylonian</hi> captivity.</p>
                     <p>Seeing the Scripture now extant exempted not <hi>Saul</hi> from violent reſiſtance which might endanger or take away his life, when the life of any of his Subjects, which he unjuſtly ſought after, could not be preſerved upon other terms, we muſt grant, unleſs we reſolve to be irrationall, that <hi>David</hi> ſinned in ſparing <hi>Saul,</hi> or elſe that his omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118326:25"/>were warranted by ſome divine precept or permiſſion which is not now extant.</p>
                     <p>No divine command or permiſſion from which there reſulted any privilege to <hi>Saul</hi> alone, or to him and thoſe who ſucceeded him in the Kingdom<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 30.11, 12, 13, 14.</note> could be longer in force then it was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Poſterity by undoubted authority.</p>
                     <p>And indeed all of the Reformed Religion acknowledge the written word of God now extant to be a ſufficient rule of our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious actions, and omiſſions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 18.</hi> The remainder of the premiſes in that Syllogiſm which is built upon <hi>Davids</hi> carriage towards <hi>Saul</hi> by thoſe who have endeavoured to ſupport Tyranny, is examined.</head>
                     <p>THe other propoſition to be examined, is, That <hi>Saul</hi> was free from humane cenſures, and violent reſiſtance: for ſo much is wont to be aſſumed as warranted by <hi>Davids</hi> carriage towards <hi>Saul.</hi> But he muſt have better eyes then ever had <hi>Lyneeus,</hi> who can ſee any thing in thoſe Texts of <hi>Samuel</hi> which I produced in the 10th Chapter, whence it may be concluded, that <hi>Saul,</hi> if he had committed ſuch ſins, as according to Gods Law were to be puniſhed with death, might not by the great Sanhedrin, (or if there had been no ſuch Court by divine inſtitution, by the major part of the people) be depoſed, and put to death, or puniſhed with death without other depoſition: unleſs there be the like reaſon that any one ſhould be exempted from humane cenſures, and from reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to be made by a private perſon, whoſe life he invadeth, which (that I may not deny it to be true) none that I have met with have urged.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall now examine, whether we may infallibly conclude from <hi>Davids</hi> teſtimony, that <hi>Sauls</hi> Subjects were bound by Gods Law rather to ſuffer themſelves to be murthered by him, then to ſlay him in their own defence.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>David</hi> expreſſeth his own judgement touching Gods will, which was contrary to the ſenſe of his followers, ſome of which undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly were not ſtrangers to the Spirit of God.</p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:118326:25"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>R. David Kimchi</hi> upon thoſe words, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>and bad me kill thee,</hi> (where our Engliſh tranſlation ſupplyeth the ſenſe by <hi>ſome,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors, by <hi>every one of my men</hi>) ſaith, <hi>And our Rabbines of bleſſed memorie interpret it, and ſay, the Scripture ſaith, when one cometh to murdor thee, conſent to kill him, as for inſtance, if a Theef be found in a Cave, as if he</hi> (David) <hi>ſhould have ſaid, I had liberty, being</hi> alſo <hi>able to kill thee, bad not my Soul ſpared thee.</hi> The ſame Doctor a little after upon thoſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> (i.e.) <hi>but</hi> mine eye <hi>ſpared thee,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Engliſh tranſlation; and according to <hi>Jonathan Ben Vriel</hi> in ſome copies, my Soul <hi>ſpared thee;</hi> according to <hi>David Kimchi,</hi> my ſoul, or mine eye <hi>ſpared thee</hi>) ſaith, <hi>It was lawfull</hi> for me <hi>to kill thee, becauſe thou didſt purſue</hi> me, and the rule is, <hi>conſent thou to kill him, that cometh to kill thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thoſe <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors which <hi>Kimchi</hi> mentioneth (and which be doth not gainſt-ſay) though they miſ-conſtrue <hi>David,</hi> yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie us that in their opinion the Scripture bad <hi>David</hi> kill <hi>Saul.</hi> And indeed ſo much was injoyned in the 6th Commandement: whether he was countermanded by God, who without doubt can diſpence with the Commandementts of the 2d. Table, according to the materialitie of them, the two laſt being excepted, I diſpute not in this place.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Abarbinel,</hi> though upon 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26, he conjectures that God by <hi>Samuel</hi> might have warned <hi>Davia</hi> to ſpare <hi>Saul,</hi> and foretold that himſelf would ſhorten his dayes, ſaw ſo little warrant from the Scripture for <hi>Davids</hi> clemencie towards <hi>Saul,</hi> that he ſaith upon Chapter 24. of the ſame book, without doubt <hi>David</hi> in his profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to his ſervants about the ſparing of <hi>Saul,</hi> and in ſlaying the <hi>Amalekite</hi> who feigned that he had killed <hi>Saul,</hi> and in putting to death thoſe who murdered <hi>Iſhboſheth,</hi> had an eye upon his own condition.</p>
                     <p>And<note n="*" place="margin">Upon 1 Sam. 24.6.</note> 
                        <hi>Ralbag</hi> alſo determineth that it was lawfull for him to have ſlain <hi>Saul,</hi> becauſe he purſued him, but ſpared him (<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>) out of an <hi>Hyperbole</hi> of clemency, and becauſe the killing of <hi>Saul</hi> would have been of bad conſequence to himſelf, who (as he knew) ſhould ſucceed in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:118326:26"/>
                     <p>That <hi>David's</hi> intereſt ſhould inſenſibly biaſe him into a tender care of Kings, was not a thing impoſſible.</p>
                     <p>Mens affections often make their judgements partiall. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Davids</hi> conſcience dictating that he ought to ſpare <hi>Saul,</hi> was erroneous? and if it was erroneous, by what means it was ſeduced, are queſtions which I ſhall not adventure to determine. But give me leave to conceive (till I ſhall be otherwiſe informed) that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> either ſinned in the ſparing of <hi>Saul,</hi> or elſe his clemency was warranted by ſome divine precept, or permiſſion, which is not now extant in the Scriptures tranſmitted to us, and which in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity was peculiarly given to <hi>David;</hi> his followers ſeem to have thought it lawfull for him to kill <hi>Saul.</hi> I doubt not but <hi>David</hi> would rather have ſlain <hi>Saul,</hi> than have ſuffered himſelf to be kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him. When he ſpared him in the Cave, he might perhaps conceive, that ſuch his clemencie (though he had no encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from <hi>Sauls</hi> former carriage to expect ſuch an event) would conciliate unto him <hi>Sauls</hi> affection; but when he again purſued him with 3000. men (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.) could not have ſo much as a ſhadow of a reaſon to harbour any hopes of a reconciliation, yet ſpared him being delivered the ſecond time into his hands. <hi>David</hi> himſelf after this repetition of his indulgence and clemency towards <hi>Saul, ſaid in his heart, I ſhall now periſh one day by the hand of</hi> Saul. Who can doubt but <hi>David</hi> ought rather to have killed <hi>Saul</hi> purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and being delivered into his hands, when in regard of his power and implacableneſs he had no other ſo probable way left him to ſecure himſelf, as by eſcaping to the Land of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> whom he had provoked by ſlaying many of their Nation, had not God by ſome precept, which is not conteined in the Scriptures now extant, injoyned him to preſerve himſelf by flight onely, and not by laying violent hands upon <hi>Saul,</hi> when it was in his power to avoid him; or at leaſt promiſed to preſerve him, though he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no violence to <hi>Saul. David,</hi> though he had a promiſe of divine protection, might <hi>ſay in his heart, All men are Liars.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:118326:26"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 19.</hi> Another Objection propounded, and anſwered.</head>
                     <p>ANother arrow out of the ſame quiver is wont to be ſhot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Abetters of the juſt liberty of the people.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Davids</hi> regrets of Conſcience for his cutting off <hi>Sauls</hi> skirt,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 24.5</note> ſeem at the firſt ſight much to countenance the impunity of Tyrants.</p>
                     <p>Some will conclude from hence, that royaltie by an eſſentiall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege is exempted from all oppoſition, ſith ſcarce any is leſſe then the cutting off the skirt of a garment.</p>
                     <p>This reaſon hath in it the more ſhew, becauſe it is not very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that God by any private admonition, which is neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, nor virtually contained in the Scripture, ſhould inhibite <hi>David</hi> from an act of no greater importance.</p>
                     <p>I anſwer, Beſides that there are many reaſons which evince that <hi>Saul,</hi> much rather then ſuch as now a dayes exerciſe Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſhould have been excepted from all manner of oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and he might perhaps have received from <hi>Samuel</hi> ſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inſtruction, out of which he concluded, that he ought not to have offered to <hi>Saul</hi> ſo much violence as the cutting off his skirt, and his own intereſt might perhaps ſomewhat bend his judgement towards the dealing gently with Kings, and his conſcience would ſtrike him as well for a ſeeming as for a reall iniquitie. The <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> Doctors tell us, that <hi>David</hi> in that action offended, becauſe he expoſed <hi>Saul</hi> in his old age to danger of taking cold, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any due end ſpoyled him of part of his garment, and was ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly puniſhed in his old age, according to what we read, 1 Kings 1.1. <hi>And they covered him with cloaths, but he gat no heat.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:118326:27"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 20.</hi> That Argument which in favour of Tyrants, is forced out of Pſalm <hi>51.6.</hi> is refuted.</head>
                     <p>THat of <hi>David</hi> in the Pſalter is wont to be alleged, as if it ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with thoſe who would place Kings above the reach of Civill Authority, <hi>Againſt thee only have I ſinned, Pſalm</hi> 51.6.</p>
                     <p>This teſtimony, if rightly underſtood, will not ſeem to exempt the Kings of the Nations, nor yet <hi>David</hi> and his ſucceſſors from humane cenſure.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>R. David Kimchi's</hi> Gloſs upon the place, is, that the thing was done inſecret, none but God being privy to it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Davids</hi> Meſſengers to <hi>Bathſheba</hi> knew not his intention in ſending for her, neither did <hi>Ioab comprehend</hi> the reaſons for which he willed the death of <hi>Vriah,</hi> men judged that he cauſed <hi>Vriah</hi> to be ſlain, becauſe he had tranſgreſſed his commandement. <hi>Kimchi Sen.</hi> the Father of this Doctor who now ſpake, thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth upon the place, <hi>Had</hi> Vriah <hi>been living, my ſin had been againſt thee and him. But ſeeing he is dead, againſt thee only have I ſinned, I confeſs to thee the ſin, becauſe all my ſin is left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, neither do I ſeek pardon of any but thee for the matter of</hi> Bathſheba <hi>and</hi> Vriah, <hi>whoſe death I cauſed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Another Author ſaith upon the place, that <hi>David</hi> accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his ſins againſt men, how great or grievous ſoever they were, as nothing in compariſon of his ſin againſt God, and therefore ſaid, <hi>Againſt thee, thee only have I ſinned.</hi> According to this gloſs, <hi>to ſin only againſt God,</hi> is the ſame that <hi>to ſin chiefly againſt him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That wrong which <hi>David</hi> had done to men, vaniſhed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appeared, being compared with that wrong which he had done to God. That which cut <hi>David</hi> to the heart, was that he had ſinned againſt God. <hi>Vbi dolor, ibi digitus. David</hi> mainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waileth the offending of ſo good, gracious, and indulgent a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     <p>When the ſame part (ſaith <hi>Hippocrates</hi>) is affected at the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118326:27"/>ſame time with ſeverall paines, the greater (ſwalloweth up) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcureth the other.</p>
                     <p>Again moſt certain it is, that ſin according to its formality is only againſt God, being a breach of his Law. Adultery and Murther had not been ſins had not God forbidden them.</p>
                     <p>Any ſinner, as well as Kings, may ſay unto God, <hi>Againſt thee only have I ſinned.</hi> Sinne, though according to its formality it be only againſt the Law of God, yet may be puniſhed by Earthly Magiſtrates, as it is hurtfull to a Common wealth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 21.</hi> The impotency of that Argument, which in favour of Tyrants is drawn from <hi>Eccleſ. 8.2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe ſecond comma, of <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8. at the firſt ſight may ſeem much to countenance Tyranny, eſpeciall in our Engliſh tranſlation, where the words are theſe, <hi>I</hi> (counſell thee) <hi>to keep the Kings commandement, and that in regard of the Oath of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Later part of the ſection is tranſlated by <hi>Coch, &amp; ſummè intentionem juramenti Dei, and chiefly the intention of the oath of God.</hi> An Oath here (as this learned Author explaineth himſelf in his notes upon the place) is whereby any one citeth God as his witneſs and judge, that with a good Conſcience, becauſe God hath ſo commanded, he will obey the King, and ſeek his good, and the good of the Common-wealth,</p>
                     <p>I doubt not but ſome will be ready to conclude from hence, that it is not lawfull upon any accompt to reſiſt the edicts of Kings.</p>
                     <p>I acknowledge that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> is capable of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, and likewiſe of that conſtruction which <hi>Coch</hi> aſſigneth it.</p>
                     <p>We may admit of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> tranſlation without detriment to the cauſe, with this provifoe, that Kings be legitimately inveſted in their authority, and be a terror to evill works, and an incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to good, and manage well the affairs of the Common-wealth.</p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:118326:28"/>
                     <p>That all theſe conditions are to be taken in, is clear from <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and the 6. and 8. Commandements.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Coch</hi> hath theſe words upon <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.2. <hi>Os Regis ſerva,</hi> h. e. <hi>fac quodcun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ex Regis ore prodit: quicquid jubet &amp; ſtatuit pro eâ poteſtate quam habet divinâ ordinatione. Regard the Kings mouth,</hi> that is, doe whatſoever he commandeth and appointeth, out of that authority which he hath by divine ordination.</p>
                     <p>No one hath from God any authority to doe evill, neither hath any one now a days a juſt title to royall authority, but through the approbation of the people.</p>
                     <p>I find in <hi>Eliſha Galico</hi> upon the place, this gloſs, <hi>I am the mouth of the King of Kings, of Jehovah, wherefore obſerve the words which I ſpeak, (and as our Doctors ſay,) becauſe thou art ſworn to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of the Law, when thou comeſt into the world, (to wit, as ſay our Doctors of bleſſed memorte) they adjure a man</hi> (in this form) <hi>Hevi tſadik veal tehi raſhaugh, be thou righteous, and be not wicked.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>One interpretation in <hi>Raſi</hi> importeth this ſenſe, <hi>I</hi> ſay <hi>it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and meet to obſerve the mouth of the King of the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we ſware unto him in</hi> Horeb, <hi>to keep his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hierome</hi> varieth but little from that interpretation which I have now propounded out of <hi>Raſi,</hi> his conſtruction of the Text running thus, <hi>Ego os Regis obſervo, &amp; praecepta juramenti Dei,</hi> I obſerve the mouth of the King, and the commandements of the oath of God. <hi>R. Levi</hi> in <hi>Midraſch</hi> hath the ſame interpretation of the beginning of the Verſe. <hi>Ani eſchmor,</hi> &amp;c. (ſaith this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor) <hi>I will obſerve the mouth of the King of Kings, that holy bleſſed one. that mouth which ſaid, I am the Lord thy God, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Another interpretation which I find in <hi>Raſi,</hi> is this, <hi>I ſay, It is meet to obſerve the commandement of the Kings of the Nations, ſo they cauſe us not to tranſgreſſe the oath which we ſware to God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Eliſha Galico</hi> (before quoted) to the ſame ſenſe, <hi>I ſay obſerve the mouth of the King, but chiefly the</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any note of an Apocope.</note> 
                        <hi>matter of the oath of God, that is, the Law which we ſware to obſerve at Mount</hi> Sinay.</p>
                     <p>Learned <hi>Broughton,</hi> and <hi>Tremellius</hi> and <hi>Junius</hi> expreſſe the ſame ſenſe, though they differ in ſome Grammaticall punctilio's.</p>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:118326:28"/>
                     <p>I ſay, regard the Kings mouth: yet after the Oath of God, <hi>Broughton.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Latter part of the verſe is rendred in Latin by the other interpreters now mentioned, <hi>Sed pro ratione juramenti Dei.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Their note upon it is thus, <hi>Moderatio obſequti quod homines de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent poteſtatibus: parendum eſt, inquit, ſed non niſi bouâ ſide &amp; conſeientiâ: quia non eſt poteſtas niſi à Deo; ac proinde jus non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet homines ab obſequio avocandi, quod Deus à ſuis jure jurando ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igit, &amp; illi ſide datâ ſe exhibituros receperunt.</hi> That which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the fourth verſe, (<hi>viz. Where the word of a King</hi> is, there is <hi>power: and who may ſay unto him, What doſt thou!</hi>) is by <hi>Eliſha Galico</hi> applyed to <hi>Iehovah</hi> the King of Kings, but is ſpoken I conceive of an earthly Prince, yet implyeth not that he is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſuch an one as may not be called to an accompt for his actions, but that we ought when he commandeth what is back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the law of God, to obey him, not only out of Religion, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> in ſuch caſes requireth our loyalty, but likewiſe out of prudence, becauſe he hath power, and beareth not the Sword in vain;<note n="*" place="margin">See Eliſha Galico <hi>upon</hi> Eccleſ. <hi>8.3.</hi>
                        </note> more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over according to ſome interpreters, that it is wiſdom in a private man, when the Magiſtrate enjoyneth what is repugnant to Gods will, to remove out of his dominions, rather then conteſt with him, which they conceive to be imported by the word <hi>Telec</hi> in the foregoing verſe.</p>
                     <p>'That it is dangerous to reſiſt Kings, becauſe they have power; is the ſenſe of that Scripture according to <hi>Abarbinel.</hi> That we ought to beware of reſiſting them, becauſe they do whatſoever pleaſeth them, is the mind of that Section, according to <hi>Eben-Ezra:</hi> The ſcope of the words is, (as I conceive comparing them with the foregoing verſes of the ſame chapter, and eſpecially with the end of the 3d. verſe) that as we tender our own ſafety, we ought not to withſtand the Magiſtrate in his edicts which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the word of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:118326:29"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. 22.</hi> The endeavours of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> towards <hi>David,</hi> and the Kings of his Family, afford no ſolid Argument to prove that Princes may not laſtfully be called to accompt, nor forcible reſiſted, when they have diſcovered themſelves to be unworthy of their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</head>
                     <p>ANother Argument by which ſome contend that Kings are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from humane cenſures, and forcible oppoſition, is drawn from the conſtant ſubmiſſion of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>David</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> and of the Tribes of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin</hi> to the Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> though by many of them they were burdened with exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive taxes, and by ſome of them with the yoak of Idolatrous wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.59.</note> to which whoſoever aſſayed to ſeduce them, was to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with death according to their municipall Laws, which were enacted immediately by the Senate-houſe of heaven.</p>
                     <p>What I have already delivered in the former Chapters, is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for the removall of this argument.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Theſe Kings had their call to government immediately from God himſelf. The Lord commanded <hi>Samuel</hi> to Anoint <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.12.</p>
                     <p>The Lord ſetled the Kingdom upon <hi>Davids</hi> poſterity, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.31, 32, 33. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.36.</p>
                     <p>If one of the Kings of the Family of <hi>David</hi> had many Sonnes, the firſt-born ſucceeded in the Kingdom, with analogy to that precept <hi>Dent.</hi> 21.17. That the eldeſt Sonne ſhould enjoy a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble portion.<note n="*" place="margin">Maimon. Hal. Malech. <hi>c. 1. Sect. 1.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>The eldeſt Sonne had the advantage of his Brethren, as well in the occupying of the Kingdom, as in the inheritance of his Fathers goods.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The firſt born alone ſucceeded in the whole authority of the Kingdom, that the honour of the Family might be preſerved en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and not be ſhattered into pieces, and that the people ſhould be ſubject to one Lord rather than to many.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> (as<note n="*" place="margin">Hal. Mcl. c. <hi>Sect. 10.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Marmamides</hi> witneſſeth) ought to have refuſed him that, in regard to his birthright, had the next title to the Crown, unleſs he was pious and feared the Lord.</p>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:118326:29"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Omnis poteſtas, &amp; omne officium in</hi> Iſrael <hi>haereditarium est ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies &amp; nepotes in aeternum; modò filius impleat locum patris ſui cum ſapientiâ &amp; pietate. Quòd ſi pietate tantum &amp; non ſapientiâ ipſi par ſit perficiunt nihilominùs officio paterno, &amp; docent id quid deeſt. At penes quem nulla eſt pietas, quamvis ſaptentiſſimus eſſet, non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movetur tamen ad ullum officierum in univerſo</hi> Iſrael.</p>
                     <p>Thus the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctor before-quoted, as he is taught to ſpeak Latine by a learned Writer, whoſe tranſlation I uſe, becauſe it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be bettered. If this Doctor ſpeak truth, it will unavoidably follow, that the wicked Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> uſed deep diſſimulation, before they were inaugurated, or that the great Sanhedrin neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected their duty, or that they wanted power to execute it.</p>
                     <p>This knot is ſomewhat moroſe, and will not eaſily be untied. The publick influence of Kingly authority might be a juſt ground of ſome exceptions from the uſuall way of hereditary propagation. The Eldeſt Sonne with the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> though he were groſſely wicked, inherited a double portion of his Fathers eſtate: we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hence conclude that the Kingdom perpetually deſcended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Eldeſt Sonne, howſoever he was qualified; becauſe it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected not ſo much one mans private benefit, as the welfare of the people.</p>
                     <p>The caſe of <hi>Solomon</hi> who was preferred before <hi>Adonijah</hi> his El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Brother, will not extricate us, in that the choice was made by God himſelf, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.5, 6, 7. Gods diſpencing with any of his poſitive Lawes, conferreth not the like privilege upon his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
                     <p>Though we are left in the dark in that <hi>Quaere,</hi> to wit, whether the <hi>Sanhedrin</hi> had authority to reject the heir apparent of the Kingdom from reigning over them for his want of religion, yet I ſhall make it clear that the Kings afore-mentioned, were more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in their authority (againſt humane oppoſition) by their call to it, then any can be by a violent invaſion thereof, or by the meer choice of men.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> were expreſly called to be Kings, and the Kingdom was ſetled upon <hi>Solomons</hi> poſterity be Gods immediate appointment, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.7. When God gave unto <hi>Ieroboam</hi> ten Tribes, he confirmed unto <hi>Solomons</hi> poſterity the Kingdom of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.36. If the Sandhedrin could lawfully hinder their
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:118326:30"/>Kings firſt-born Sonne from reigning over them, when he was not an heir of his Fathers virtues, that autority was given them by Gods Commandement, or permiſſion: and it ſhould remain that they were determined by God himſelf to preferre to the Kingdom him that had the next title by diſcent being duely qualified, and one of <hi>Solomons</hi> poſterity, though all of them were egregiouſly wicked.</p>
                     <p>God ſecured the Kingdom for <hi>Solomons</hi> poſterity againſt thoſe iniquities wherewith they ſhould provoke his divine Majeſtie, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.14.15.16. That the grant of the Kingdom was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall as to <hi>Saul,</hi> is cleared by that Scripture, and by 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11.36. The Hiſtory of the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> informeth us, that ſome of them provoked God as deeply as did <hi>Saul,</hi> from whom he took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Kingdom. God did not preſerve them from provoking him as did <hi>Saul:</hi> but ſhewed them more viſible favour, by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing the Kingdom in their poſterity. That condition which is expreſſed in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.7. in thoſe words, <hi>I will eſtabliſh his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for ever, if he be conſtant to doe my Commandements, and my judgments, as at this day;</hi> had reſpect unto the Kingdom, as it was entire over the 12 Tribes, but not to every part of it; as we may gather from what hath been ſpoken, and by comparing it with 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 12, &amp; 13. That of the Pſalmiſt (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.12.) If thy children will keep my Covenant and my teſtimony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth that <hi>Davids</hi> poſteritie, unleſſe they revolted from God (as did <hi>Solomon</hi>) ſhould reigne over the 12 Tribes, but moreover that their Line and Succeſſion ſhould not be interrupted (as it was for the King of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> and ſome other of their Kings) by capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, untill the coming of <hi>Shiloh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here it may be inquired, how the eſtabliſhing of <hi>Davids</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for ever, which is promiſed 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.16. can conſiſt with thoſe events which have befaln his poſterity; as the <hi>Babylonian</hi> captivity, and the bereaving of them of all outward and viſible Dominion.</p>
                     <p>That I may not confine the promiſe to Chriſts ſpirituall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the word <hi>Olam,</hi> which is there uſed, doth not alwayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note eternity, or a duration till the end of the World; but in generall a duration hidden from man, whether infinite or finite.</p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:118326:30"/>
                     <p>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>See</hi> Munster de ſide Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum.</note>Part of the Ceremoniall Law is ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for ever,</hi> Numb. 10.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>for ever,</hi> Exod. 21.6. is <hi>till the next Jubilee,</hi> according to <hi>Raſi, Aben-Ezra, Bechai,</hi> and <hi>Abarbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> upon thoſe words, and the <hi>Talmud</hi> in <hi>Kiduſhin. Abarbinel</hi> telleth us that becauſe 50 yeers were counted one <hi>Age,</hi> or <hi>Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> the fiftieth yeer which is the yeer of <hi>Jubilee,</hi> is called <hi>Olam.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>According to his conſtruction <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſhall ſupply the place of<note n="*" place="margin">See Pſal. 18.50.</note> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: and indeed it is wont to ſignifie <hi>ad,</hi> which is thence derived. But I ſhould rather conceive that <hi>for ever</hi> there according to the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall accompt, is the ſame that for the preſent generation.</p>
                     <p>The Servant whoſe Ear was bored thorow, when the generation was renewed (as <hi>Aben-Ezra</hi> ſpeaketh) to wit, in the year of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilee</hi> was to be ſet at liberty.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>For ever,</hi> in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.7. ſeemeth to ſignifie the time in which the Ceremoniall Law ſhould continue in force. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>For evermore,</hi> is untill <hi>Shiloh come,</hi> Pſal. 132.12.</p>
                     <p>We cannot determine out of thoſe Scriptures before-quoted, to wit, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.31, 32, 33, 1 <hi>King</hi> 11.36. Whether <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> and the Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> were liable to depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and capitall puniſhment by their Subjects for tyranny, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and other groſs delinquencies, without an expreſſe permiſſion or injunction from God.</p>
                     <p>God might puniſh their perſons in ſuch ſort, yet not cauſe <hi>his mercy to depart from them, as he took it away from</hi> Saul, whoſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity he ſecluded from ſucceeding in the Kingdom.</p>
                     <p>But it is clear that thoſe Kings had a large advantage (as I ſhewed before concerning <hi>Saul</hi>) being compared with ſuch as came to a Kingdom meerly by Conqueſt, or by humane choice, in that they were not liable to depoſition, ſo long as their carriage was worthy of their office.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Abarbinel</hi> expreſſeth the ſame ſenſe in his Preface to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon 2 Sam. 15. <hi>Abſalom</hi> (ſaith he there) <hi>intended not to ſlay David, neither aſcended it into his heart, neither did Iſrael agree at all to rebell against their King, and to kill him: farre be it from them, for who ſhall ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords anointed, and be guiltleſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The other two Arguments, which I uſed againſt ſuch as denyed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118326:31"/>
                        <hi>Saul</hi> to be privileged above the Kings of other Nations, in the 16. and 17 Chapter, make equually for <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> and the Kings of <hi>Iudah.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If <hi>Saul</hi> and the Kings of the Family of <hi>David</hi> were exempted from depoſition, and capitall puniſhment, and forcible reſiſtance, yet not by a common Crown-privilege, but by a ſpeciall grant from God, directly expreſſed, or at leaſt implied by the manner of their call to the Kingdom, and ſome other reaſons which were peculiar to them.</p>
                     <p>This aſſertion hath already been ſufficiently confirmed, but is much countenanced alſo<note n="*" place="margin">See Chap. 6.</note> by the demeanour of the <hi>Iews</hi> towards their Kings which were not of the Family of <hi>David,</hi> in the times of the ſecond Temple.</p>
                     <p>Another reaſon for which <hi>David</hi> with his ſucceſſors of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage ſeem to have been privileged above the Kings of other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is that they were types of chriſt, whoſe Kingdom ſhould endure:</p>
                     <p>It is very conſiderable likewiſe that the Sanhedrin, and that ſuch among the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> as deſired a reformation in the Church or State, or both, might want ſtrength to oppoſe their Kings; and that through the juſt ordination of divine Providence, in that they had preferred earthly Kings before the Monarch of heaven and earth. Neither can I doubt but the major part of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would the rather bear with wicked Kings in that themſelves were addicted to the like wickedneſs.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall now examine what the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors ſay in this point touching matter of right, and what the Scripture witneſſeth touching matter of fact. <hi>The kings of the Family of</hi> David <hi>judge and are judged,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Babylonian Talmud</hi> in the <hi>tractate</hi> of the <hi>Miſchnah</hi> called Sanhedr. Chapt. 2. Sect 2.</p>
                     <p>That the Kings of the Family of <hi>David</hi> were not exempted from that Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.2. which required that a certain number of ſtripes ſhould be inflicted upon thoſe who deſerved to be beaten, but were for certain faults liable to it, is affirmed by <hi>Mabimon Hal. Melach.</hi> c. 3. Sect. 4. in the <hi>Talmud</hi> Sanhedr. c. 19. and in other Tractates thereof, and in ſeverall other writings of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors.</p>
                     <p>That thoſe who reigned over the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> were as obnoxious
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:118326:31"/>to cenſure for ſome other faults, as for thoſe three which were wont to be reckoned up by the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors, viz. <hi>the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of Wives, Gold and Silver, and Horſes;</hi> is ſo clear to ſuch as will not <hi>jurare in verba Magiſtrorum,</hi> that it needeth no proof.</p>
                     <p>Neither could this Law be executed without the endangering of their lives in caſe they reſiſted. If the Kings of the <hi>Iews</hi> for mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying Wives, Gold and Silver, and horſes, were to be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with ſtripes, then by the rule of proportion for the greateſt fault with death, and they might be depoſed when they were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly wicked, as the next heir of the Kingdom might by his wickedneſs be debarred from reigning, unleſs they were exempted for the reaſons before mentioned, which agrees not to any Princes now a dayes.</p>
                     <p>God foretelleth in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. how their Kings ſhould demean themſelves, but doth not there or elſewhere authoriſe them to uſe ſuch acts of violence.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Miſchpat</hi> in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.11. ſignifieth the <hi>Manner</hi> or <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> as in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.13. not <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> as in c. 10.25.</p>
                     <p>That the Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> were not liable to be cenſured by the Sanhedrin in ſuch manner as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors affirm, becauſe we read not in the Scripture that they were ſo cenſured, or becauſe they never were ſo cenſured, is an argument not ſo ſubſtantive but it will fall of it ſelf, without oppoſition. We may conclude much rather that we ought to aſſent to that piece of hiſtory in thoſe writers, in that it is not contradicted in the word of God? ſome of them (I conjecture) had been brought to their trialls and cenſures by the Sanhedrin, <hi>niſi impunitatis Cupido retinuiſſet, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis ſemper conatibus adverſa.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That I may now ſpeak touching matter of fact, we ſhall find in the practice of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in the times of <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Rehodoam,</hi> and <hi>Iehoram,</hi> might we lawfully make the examples of actions and omiſſions, our rules; enough to warrant the taking up of Arms againſt Kings, when they neglect the executing of juſtice, or ſqueeſe their Subjects by immoderate taxes, or impoſe upon them too hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy ſervitude.</p>
                     <p>That method which <hi>Abſolom</hi> uſed to ſteal away he peoples hearts from his Father, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.2, 3, 4. being compared with
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:118326:32"/>his ſucceſſe, maketh us conjecture that thoſe who joyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to him in the conſpiracy, thought it lawfull for them to wreſt authority out of <hi>Davids</hi> hands, and to ſettle it upon <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom</hi> by the ſword, that juſtice might be more freely diſpenced. <hi>David</hi> was old, neither deputed any, (if we may believe <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi>) to hear thoſe who had controverſies with other men. <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> promiſeth that he, were he made judge in the Land, would do juſtice; and meant, as it is probable, by himſelf immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not by his miniſters. It appeareth that they intended not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſtrip <hi>David</hi> of his Authority, but alſo to take away his life, from 2. &amp; 4. verſes of the 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. compared together. <hi>Abarbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> conceiveth that neither <hi>Abſolom,</hi> nor the Elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> nor the reſt of the People who ſided with him in the conſpiracie, had any thought to deveſt <hi>David</hi> of his Crown and Dignity, but to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute <hi>Abſolom</hi> to him for the executing of the Royall Authority during his life, and for his ſucceſſor afterwards. <hi>Abſolom</hi> was induced (ſaith this Doctour) to that attempt, becauſe <hi>David</hi> had ſworn unto <hi>Bathſheba</hi> that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſhould reign after him, and ſit on his Throne in his ſtead, as alſo becauſe he ſuſpected that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> would cauſe <hi>Solomon</hi> to be placed in the Kingdom during his own life, and after he was once King, who ſhould ſay unto him, what doeſt thou?</p>
                     <p>The people conſented to <hi>Abſolom</hi> (ſaith the ſame Author) becauſe he was <hi>Davids</hi> eldeſt Son after the death of <hi>Amnon,</hi> and was of the fitteſt age both to judge them, and to fight their Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, to with about<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Raſi</hi> &amp; R. <hi>Kim.</hi> faſten the epocha of the 40. years which are mentioned 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.7. In the <hi>Iraelites</hi> asking a King of <hi>Samuel;</hi> and <hi>Kimchi</hi> addeth that <hi>Saul</hi> reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with <hi>Samuel</hi> 1 year, and two years alone, and that the other 37 years belonged to the reign of <hi>David. Ralbag</hi> and <hi>R. Ieſchaiah</hi> make mention of this opinion, but ſeem to have thought that the 40 years began with <hi>Davids</hi> Kingdom, <hi>Ralbag</hi> alſo conjectureth that it was propheſied of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Kingdom that it ſhould ſtand only 40 years, and <hi>Abſolom</hi> concluded theſe years now expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the Kingdom ſhould depart from <hi>david,</hi> and that he ſhould bring to paſſe his Intention of killing him. Theſe 40 years (ſaith <hi>Abarbinel</hi>) could not begin at <hi>Sauls</hi> inauguration, for that was above 50 years paſt. He reckoneth that <hi>David</hi> had reigned al moſt 40 years, and that <hi>Abſolom</hi> was born at <hi>Hebron</hi> in the beginning of <hi>Davids</hi> Kingdom.</note> 40 years, and becauſe they were diſaffected towards <hi>Solomon,</hi> both by reaſon of <hi>Davids</hi> Adultery with <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba,</hi> and his killing of <hi>Vriah,</hi> and likewiſe that he was but a Child about 9 years old, that is, becauſe they thought him unfit to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, and feared a curſe upon his Government in regard of the ſins of his Parents.</p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:118326:32"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ahithophel</hi> (according to the ſame commentator) conjectured<note n="*" place="margin">Not much unlike to this is the delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Ioab,</hi> in the Author now prayſed, who ſuſpected ſhould <hi>Abſolom</hi> be ſuffered to eſcape with life his Father might perhaps make him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his eldeſt Son his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor in the Kingdom, and himſelf ſhould be the Butt for his enmlty and hatted.</note> that <hi>David,</hi> to buy his peace would conſent that <hi>Abſolom</hi> his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Son ſhould ſucceed him in the Kingdom, and that he would retain an enmity and hatred againſt himſelf, and therefore ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted ſuch Counſels, as might debar a reconciliation, and cut off <hi>David.</hi> His advice in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.21. tended to the preventing of all thoughts touching a reconciliation (but moreover to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind the people of <hi>Davids</hi> ſin with <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and to beget in them an expectation of divine revenge to be executed upon <hi>David,</hi> wherein they ſhould be much confirmed by <hi>Nathans</hi> prophecie, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.11, 12.) and that other part of his Counſell in the 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.1, 2. to the taking away of <hi>Davids</hi> life.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Abſolom</hi> (ſaith the ſame Author) conſented to the former part of <hi>Ahithophel's</hi> advice, which was that he ſhould go in unto his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Concubines, leſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhould revolt from him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he perfected an agreement with his father: but the other part of his Counſell, which was to kill <hi>David,</hi> he abhorred, and therefore conſulted with <hi>Huſhai,</hi> and preferred his advice.</p>
                     <p>The ſame Doctour ſaith upon 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.4. that it pleaſed <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom</hi> and the elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that <hi>Anithophel</hi> and the young men ſhould go after <hi>David,</hi> but <hi>Abſolom</hi> did not acquieſce in <hi>Ahitho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel's</hi> adviſing him to ſmite David, and therefore inquired the judgement of <hi>Huſhai.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But the Scripture affordeth no hint for <hi>Abſoloms</hi> diſliking of any part of <hi>Ahithophel's</hi> counſell, before he had conſulted with <hi>Huſhai.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Were <hi>Abarbinel</hi> right in his conjecture, yet the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> thought it lawfull to tranſlate by violence the exerciſe of Royall authority from <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Abſolom,</hi> wherefore ſcarce any Prince though of <hi>Methuſelah's</hi> years, would deſire to be disburthened: and to appoint their King a ſucceſſor againſt his mind, though he were a Prophet, and therefore likely to have received punctuall inſtructions from God touching the propagation of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
                     <p>The ten tribes rebelled againſt <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> becauſe he would not abate ſomewhat of the grievous ſervitude which his Father had impoſed upon them, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 10. Their revolting is not reſolved into <hi>Ahijahs</hi> prophecie, but the harſh anſwer which <hi>Rehoboam</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to them.</p>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:118326:33"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Libnah</hi> revolted from <hi>Jehoram,</hi> becauſe he had forſaken the Lord God of his Fathers, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.10. But ſee eſpecially the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances before produced in the tenth Chapter.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="addendum">
                     <head>To be inſerted in Chapter <hi>9.</hi> after thoſe words, <hi>From violence.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Whilſt people are Malignant, they are not to be permitted to ſuffrage in ſtate affairs, neither indeed would it become them, or prove for their welfare: for <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>ſervilis pravitas,</hi> as <hi>Plato</hi> in <hi>Alcibade primo,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Caeterùm antequam virtus adſit, Conducit viro, non ſolùm puero, regià meliore, quam regere, Plato ibid.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But as ſoon as they are reformed, they ought to be truſted with their votes: for <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Liberalis virtus. ibid.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="addendum">
                     <head>
                        <hi>This to be inſerted in Chap.</hi> 9. <hi>after theſe Words,</hi> can give no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a title to authority, than theſt to another mans Goods.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mem.</hi> That what I have out <hi>Elias Levita,</hi> and <hi>Broughton,</hi> who undoubtedly followed him, (in Chap. 17. p. l.) to be contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as it faſtneth upon <hi>Ezra</hi> the collecting of the Scripture into one body. That probably was needleſs.</p>
                     <p>I cannot conſent to <hi>Ariſt.</hi> telling us, (<hi>Polit.</hi> l. 1. c. 8.) that a War undertaken to compell men to ſubjection, who being more fit to obey then to command, are unwilling to ſubmit themſelves to ſuch as are more able to govern, is agreeable to the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and putting no difference in point of juſtice between the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing of theſe and the hunting of Wild beaſts.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118326:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <q> Behold the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this Age.</q>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <l>If thou obſerv'ſt theſe Rules, and tak'ſt my Phyſick,</l>
                  <l>'Twill keep thee from the Pox, Plague, Cough, or Tyſick,</l>
                  <l>Conſumptions, Dropſies, nay, the truth to tell ye,</l>
                  <l>From all griefes either i'th'head; back, or belly.</l>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
